<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Animadversions upon Lillies grammar, or Lilly scanned An extract of grammaticall problemes. Gathered out of the inquiries, and disputes of the most judicious grammarians. Set downe by way of question, and answere. ...</title>
            <author>Wise, Thomas, M.A.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1625</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15602</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25867</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101876</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837679</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837679</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2017</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15602)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2017)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1017:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Animadversions upon Lillies grammar, or Lilly scanned An extract of grammaticall problemes. Gathered out of the inquiries, and disputes of the most judicious grammarians. Set downe by way of question, and answere. ...</title>
                  <author>Wise, Thomas, M.A.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 144+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby for Richard Hawkins, and are to be sold at his shop in Chancerie Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1625.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Thomas Wise.</note>
                  <note>At least the Bodleian Library and the Harvard University Library have an extra leaf with an address to the reader and errata--STC.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacking all after page 144.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2017:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2017:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANIMADVERSIONS VPON <hi>LILLIES</hi> GRAMMAR, OR LILLY SCANNED. <hi>An Extract of Grammaticall</hi> PROBLEMES. Gathered out of the Inquiries, and <hi>Diſputes of the moſt judicious</hi> GRAMMARIANS. Set downe by way of Queſtion, and Anſwere. <hi>Wherein,</hi> Many difficult Knots in the <hi>Engliſh Rudiments,</hi> and <hi>Lillies Grammar</hi> are vnlooſed: many Obſcurities enlightned: many Errors and Incogitancies diſcouered: many Deficiences ſupplied, the Originall and Reaſon of many Termes of Art manifeſted, and not a few acceſſorie Queſtions diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſed with much breuitie and perſpicuitie. <hi>Very neceſſarie, and profitable for all thoſe that deſire to be exact Grammarians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>W. Stansby</hi> for <hi>Richard Hawkins,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in Chancerie Lane. 1625.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2017:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2017:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Animaduerſions vpon</hi> LILLIES Grammar, OR LILLY ſcanned. <hi>An Extract of Grammaticall</hi> PROBLEMES.</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of <hi>Grammar,</hi> and the parts thereof.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ay euery one that teacheth</hi> Lillies <hi>Grammar, bee called</hi> Grammaticus <hi>in proprietie of ſpeech?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: If he be able to teach thoſe <hi>Rudiments</hi> onely, he is rather to be called <hi>Grammatiſta?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What difference is there betweene</hi> Grammatiſta, <hi>and</hi> Grammaticus?</p>
               <p>Among the Ancients he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Grammaticus,</hi> who did not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teach how to ſpeake a tongue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2017:3"/> well, but alſo did examine, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe all the difficulties in Poets, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians, Orators, Philoſophers, &amp;c. hee that taught the Elements of Words, Letters, was called <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiſta. Grammaticus</hi> with them was as much as <hi>Literatus,</hi> a learned Scholar, or Criticke, whom we now call a<note n="*" place="margin">Philologi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diunt Ludouicus Viues Iulius Scaliger, Caſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonus, nec non Ben. Ionſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ius Poetarum facile princeps, &amp; non ſine doctrinae, &amp; humanitatis ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norifica praefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione nominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Ioh. Seldenus.</note> 
                  <hi>Philologer; Grammatiſta</hi> as much as <hi>Literator,</hi> an Elementarie <hi>Pedant.</hi> They differ in effect as much as a Fidler, and an exact Muſitian. <hi>Sueton. de claris Grammaticis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May that ſpeech, which is compared according to the rules of Grammar, bee called</hi> congrua oratio, <hi>in the proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the latine tongue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So it is commonly called by moſt Schoole-maſters: but to ſpeake pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly; <hi>loqui congruè,</hi> is to ſpeake fitly, and oppoſitly to the purpoſe, which is the part of a Logician, an Orator, a Moraliſt: but to ſpeake according to rule, is, <hi>Grammaticè loqui,</hi> which is not oppoſed to <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barè loqui</hi> (for there may bee a rude impoliſht and barbarous expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where there is no breach of rule,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2017:3"/> and <hi>Priſcians</hi> head is vntoucht) but to <hi>caſtigate,</hi> or <hi>tersè,</hi> or <hi>emendatè lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui,</hi> to ſpeake trimly and elegantly, according to the example of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Authors; according to that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Aliud est Grammaticè, aliud la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinè loqui: Congruè loqui,</hi> reſpects the fitneſſe of the matter; <hi>Emendate lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui,</hi> the puritie of the ſtile; <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticè loqui,</hi> the regularitie of the conſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that diuiſion of Grammar into foure parts,</hi> Orthographia, Etymol. Syntaxis, Proſop. <hi>an exact diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Priſcian, Melancthon,</hi> and their followers ſo diuided Grammar: but<note n="g" place="margin">Craſsè.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rather then<note n="h" place="margin">Exactè.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, it may more artificially and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly bee diuided into two parts, <hi>Etymologie</hi> and <hi>Syntaxis:</hi> for theſe two doe, as integrall parts, take vp the whole body of Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar: the other two, <hi>Orthogr.</hi> and <hi>Proſodia,</hi> like Particles are contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in theſe, and ſpread through the whole Grammar.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:2017:4"/>
               <head>Of ORTHOGRAPHIE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IS Orthographie ſtill the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: It hath beene often chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and therfore the rule of it muſt be cuſtome. The Hebrewes, Syrians, and Arabians, begin to write from the right hand to the left. They of China, from the top of the leafe to the bottome in a direct line. Other Nations, from the left hand to the right, which motion of the hand ſeemes to be moſt naturall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Letters.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>How are diphthongs made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the diuerſe diſpoſitions of the vowels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whence haue the diphthongs their names?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the Greeke words <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>bis,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>loquor;</hi> becauſe there is a conflation, and coalition of two vowels in a diphthong, which are to bee vttered and breathed out as one entire ſyllable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the meaning of that paſſage
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2017:4"/> in the firſt page of</hi> Lillies <hi>Grammar? S, ſuae cuiuſdam potestatis litera eſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lilly</hi> hauing diuided the Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants into Mutes, as <hi>b, c, d, &amp;c.</hi> and ſemi-vowels, as <hi>l, m, n, r, ſ, x, z,</hi> he ſubdiuideth the ſemi-vowels into liquids, and double conſonants, and ſince <hi>(ſ)</hi> will not be changed in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe rankes, hee calleth it <hi>ſuae cuiuſdam poteſtatis literam;</hi> ſuch a letter as is (as it were) of its owne head, ſits by it ſelfe, will not be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalled in that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>literarum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why are</hi> x <hi>and</hi> z <hi>called,</hi> literae du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices?</p>
               <p>Becauſe they haue the force of two conſonants, as <hi>x</hi> may be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into <hi>Cs,</hi> or <hi>gs,</hi> as appeares by the genitiue caſes of nounes ending in <hi>x, Rex, Regis, Dux, Ducis. z</hi> is chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (being a greeke letter original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) into <hi>ss,</hi> as <hi>Maſſa,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſſo,</hi> of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many wayes is the letter</hi> (I) <hi>taken?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three wayes: as in this word <hi>ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunium:</hi> in the firſt ſyllable, <hi>I</hi> is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a ſimple conſonant, in the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2017:5"/> ſecond for a double one, in the third for a vowell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How doth it appeare that</hi> (I) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two vowels, is a double conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe the Ancients, in ſtead of <hi>Maior, Peior,</hi> were wont expreſly to write <hi>Maijor, Peijor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hath</hi> (I) <hi>betweene two vowels al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the force of a double conſonant, as</hi> Lilly <hi>tells vs here, and in the rules of Quantitie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: The rule is true only in ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple words, not in words compound, for in ſuch wee finde the ſyllable which comes immediately before <hi>I</hi> between two vowels, made ſhort in the Poets: as in <hi>Bijugis, Quadrijugus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Martis equi bijuges, &amp; magni cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus Achillis.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Virg.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Centum quadrijugos agitabo ad flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina currus.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Idem.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lilly</hi> in the diuiſion of his letters, tells vs, that two is a ſemi-vowell: how then comes it to paſſe, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non after he ſaith, <hi>y</hi> &amp; <hi>z, latinis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionibus nunquam admiſcentur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is very ſtrange a man ſhould ſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2017:5"/> ſoone forget himſelfe: there is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt contradiction, from which I cannot acquit him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not</hi> k <hi>or</hi> y <hi>mixed amongst o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther latine letters, as</hi> Lilly <hi>affirmes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>K</hi> is iudged by the modern Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians to bee an vnprofitable let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but<note n="*" place="margin">Haec tribus in Latio tantum addita nomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> 
                  <hi>Auſonius</hi> ſaith, it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed before three latine wordes: which ſome aſſigne to bee, <hi>Kaput,</hi> a Chapter, <hi>Kalendae, Kalumnia:</hi> and as for <hi>y,</hi> if it be not mixed amongſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine letters, how is it that wee finde in <hi>Propria quae maribus, Tybris, Lybs, Tybur:</hi> proper names, <hi>Phryx, Gryps, Hydrops, Syren, Hyems, &amp;c.</hi> appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues: nay, how is it that in the very ſame page, where hee affirmes this, we finde theſe words: <hi>Hymnus, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyllaba, Hieronymus.</hi> Here as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, <hi>bonus dormitat Lilius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the</hi> literae majuſculae <hi>put for when they are ſet alone?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> for <hi>Aulus,</hi> as <hi>A. Gellius; Aulus G.</hi> but ſome Criticks write <hi>Agellius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>B.</hi> among the Schoole-men, is put for <hi>Beatus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>C. V. <hi>Celſitudo Veſtra.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:2017:6"/>
               <p>C. M. <hi>Caeſarea Maieſtas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>D. <hi>Diuus.</hi> Doctor, <hi>Dominus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>E. T. <hi>Excellentia Tua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I C. <hi>Iureconſultus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>M. <hi>Marcus,</hi> and <hi>Magiſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>N. <hi>Nomen ignotum, vel Nota.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. C. <hi>Patres Conſcripti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. L. <hi>Poeta Laureatus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. C. <hi>Poeta Coronatus,</hi> vel <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Comes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>R. <hi>Rabbi.</hi> R. T. D. <hi>Reuerenda Tua Dignitas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Sanctus.</hi> S. P. D. <hi>Salutem plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimam dicit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S C. <hi>Senatuſconſultum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>V.C. <hi>Vrbs condita &amp;c.</hi> vid. <hi>Lilium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not a great decorum to bee obſerued in the Poets, by the repetition of diuers letters, to expreſſe to the life the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters themſelues?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes. <hi>E.</hi> ſerues to expreſſe lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and ſorrow: as, <hi>Lachrymae peredere humore exangues genas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>F.</hi> To expreſſe blowing: as, <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras turbine perflant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I.</hi> To expreſſe thin, and peircing things. <hi>Accipiunt inimicum imbrem, nimiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fatiſcunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2017:6"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>L.</hi> To expreſſe lowe, and ſoft things.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Qualem virgineo demeſeum pollice florem</l>
                  <l>Seu mollis violae, ſeu languentis Hiacynthi.
<bibl>
                        <hi>Virg.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>M.</hi> To expreſſe great things: as, <hi>Dorſum immane mart ſummo:</hi> as alſo to expreſſe admiration. <hi>Deum im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalem! hominum! fidem!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>N.</hi> hath a contrarie vſe; it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts. <hi>Frangitur in<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſinus ſcindit ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe vnde reductos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R.</hi> To expreſſe fury, and anger; and rough, and terrible things. <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precor arma armis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S.</hi> By this <hi>Virgil</hi> deſcribes the noiſe of a tempeſt, <hi>Emiſſam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> hye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem ſenſit Neptunus, &amp; imis ſtagnae refuſa vadis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>T.</hi> To expreſſe ſlowneſſe: as, <hi>Nec nos obniti contra, nec tendere tantum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>V.</hi> To expreſſe obſcure things: <hi>Tu plaeuſu, fremitu<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> virum, ſtudijſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fauentûm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What wordes are to bee written with great letters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Proper names, and ſuch as are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2017:7"/> thence deriued, and the names of Arts.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beginnings of Sentences in Proſe and Verſes in Poems.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Names of Offices, and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it lawfull to mixe letters of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue with latine letters?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes ſomtimes, but very ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: as, <hi>Liber phraſe<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>n, ſignum dioe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>réſe<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Syllables.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can we ſay that</hi> ea, ei, <hi>and</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>are words of two and three ſyllables, when as they conſiſt only of vowels ſimply, and ſeuerally pronounced?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee may for want of a better terme: but properly <hi>ſyllaba</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> .i. <hi>concipere,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a comprehenſion or vniting of diuers letters in pronuntiation with one tone, or ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many letters hath the largest ſyllable in the latine tongue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not aboue ſixe: as <hi>ſtirps.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2017:7"/>
               <head>Of the diſtinction of Syllables.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>What rules haue you for the distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or diuiſion of Syllables?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Diuers: firſt, in the diuiſion of a word, thoſe letters are to be ioyned together, which may bee ioyned in the beginning of a word: as in <hi>Magnus Aruſpex,</hi> the laſt ſyllables muſt bee <hi>gnus</hi> and <hi>ſpex,</hi> becauſe <hi>gn</hi> and <hi>ſp</hi> may bee found in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of words, as <hi>gnatus, ſpectrum.</hi> Secondly, if a ſingle conſonant bee put in the midle betwixt two vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, it ſhall belong to the latter, as <hi>Pa-ter:</hi> if two conſonants be gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, the firſt belongs to the firſt ſyllable, the latter to the latter, as <hi>An-nus.</hi> Thirdly, if the latter ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable begin with a vowell, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſhall end in a vowell, as <hi>De-us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth not the ſecond rule ſometimes faile?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, in compoſition, as <hi>ab-utor,</hi> the former ſyllable ends in a conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, the latter begins with a vowel; ſo <hi>abs-temius,</hi> of <hi>abs</hi> and <hi>temetum.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2017:8"/>
               <head>Of Pronuntiation.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whence hath a tone its name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſcrew vp, or ſlacken the ſtrings of an inſtrument of muſick. As by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, or remiſſion of the ſtrings the ſound is flat, or ſharp: ſo accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the tone, or accent a ſyllable is ſhrilly, or depreſſedly pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In a word, whoſe</hi> penultima ſyllaba <hi>is doubtfull, or common, where is the accent to be put?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the <hi>antepenultima,</hi> as <hi>Célebris, Medíocris, Vólucris, Fúnebris,</hi> thus in Proſe; but in Verſe, the accent is according to the meaſure: as <hi>Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, pictae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> volúcres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is the accent to be plac't in</hi> antepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nultima <hi>in theſe words:</hi> Deinde, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde, perinde, aliquando, ſiquando, nequando, hucvſque, &amp;c. <hi>as</hi> Lilly <hi>would haue it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for it is an vndoubted rule receiued amongſt the beſt Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians. <hi>Polyſyllaba, quae habent pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nultimam poſitione longam penultimam
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2017:8"/> acuunt vt deinceps, duntáxat, probléma, extémplo:</hi> and herein <hi>Lilly</hi> thwarts his owne third generall rule of Tones: and hee is thwarted by <hi>Quint. Inſtit. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. where he ſaith, <hi>Duabus longis ſequentibus primam acui noſter ſermo non patitur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haue</hi> propémodum, ádmodum, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilóminus <hi>the acute accent in</hi> antepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nultima, <hi>for this reaſon only, to distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh them from</hi> prope-modum, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum, nihilo-minus, <hi>as</hi> Lilly <hi>beares vs in hand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: but the reaſon why they are ſo accented, is, becauſe theſe by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition being made one word, haue their <hi>penultima</hi> ſhort by quantitie.</p>
               <p>Lilly <hi>tells vs, that</hi> duntaxat, dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps, deorſum, <hi>haue the accent in</hi> ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penultima, <hi>to difference them from other words: Is that aſſertion true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for wee reade no where <hi>dun taxat, dein ceps, de orſum,</hi> as diſtinct words, as <hi>per inde, pro inde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is</hi> amabo <hi>the aduerbe of flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be pronounced?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some pronounce it <hi>ámabo,</hi> to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh it from the verb <hi>amato,</hi> but bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2017:9"/> authoritie teacheth vs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce <hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>mábo:</hi> as, <hi>Dic verum mihi Marce dic amabo. Mart.</hi> where <hi>ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo</hi> hath the <hi>penultima</hi> long by quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is</hi> Ti <hi>before another vowell to be pronounced?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alwayes as in the word <hi>Oratio,</hi> where <hi>(t)</hi> doth <hi>liqueſcere,</hi> and is to be pronounced as <hi>z,</hi> as if it were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>orazio,</hi> except firſt, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of a word, as <hi>tiara:</hi> ſecondly, if <hi>ſ</hi> come before it, as <hi>iuſtior:</hi> thirdly, in the poeticall infinitiues, as <hi>mittier:</hi> fourthly, in borrowed words, as <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litía, pragmatía.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How are Greeke words, being made latine, to be pronounced?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According to their Quantitie, not according to the tone, or accent they had in their owne tongue: as, we are not to pronounce <hi>Nicódemus,</hi> but <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codémus;</hi> not <hi>Demónicus,</hi> but <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nícus;</hi> not <hi>Basílius,</hi> but <hi>Baſilíus;</hi> not <hi>Caeſárea,</hi> but <hi>Caeſaréa;</hi> not <hi>Eúbulus,</hi> but <hi>Eubúlus:</hi> for the <hi>penultima</hi> of theſe is long by quantitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2017:9"/>
               <head>Of the Quantitie of Syllables.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are we to write</hi> patrizo, <hi>as</hi> Lilly <hi>doth in the rule concerning words long by poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or</hi> patriſſo.</p>
               <p>I thinke we are rather to write <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſſo</hi> for <hi>z</hi> is not a letter proper to the latine tongue and I find other verbes of imitation ending in <hi>ſſo,</hi> as <hi>Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſo, Philoniſſo, Atticiſſo:</hi> nay, <hi>Lilly</hi> himſelfe ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h in his rules of the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of verbes. <hi>Imitatiua ſunt &amp;c. vt Patriſſo &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that rule,</hi> vocalis breuis ante mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ſequente liquida communis red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, <hi>to be vnderſtood indifferently, and equally of all the foure liquids,</hi> l, m, n, r?</p>
               <p>No: but of <hi>(l)</hi> and <hi>(r)</hi> very often, of <hi>(m)</hi> and <hi>(n)</hi> very ſeldome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When of</hi> l <hi>and</hi> r?</p>
               <p>In ſimple words, or ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pounds whoſe mutes together with the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quids pertaine to the ſame ſyllable: and this is very neceſſarie to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued for theſe words; <hi>obrodo, obrepo, obligo, obrumpo &amp;c.</hi> though they haue a ſhort vowell before a mute, and a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2017:10"/> liquid, yet are they long, and are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer found ſhort, for as much as the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid and mute in any of them, being compound words, doe not concurre to the conſtitution of a ſyllable: for theſe words are to be diuided, thus: <hi>ob-rodo, ob-repo,</hi> as appeares by the rules of <hi>diſtinction</hi> of ſyllable before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When of</hi> m <hi>and</hi> n?</p>
               <p>In Greek words, as <hi>Cygnus, Progne, Atlas,</hi> or ſuch as imitate greek words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Giue ſome examples of</hi> l, r, <hi>put after liquids, making the precedent ſyllables common?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>L</hi> is put after mutes in theſe words, <hi>Hybla, Agathocles, Abodlas, Ciniflo, Noegla, Locuples, Atlas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>R</hi> in theſe, <hi>Celebris, Volucris, Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra, Africa, Denigno, Apri, Arbitror.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why is the laſt ſyllable ſaue one in</hi> Caï, Vultei, Pompei, &amp;c. <hi>long in Poets, whereas as one vowell comes before an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lillies</hi> Grammar doth not except theſe wordes from the generall rule <hi>vocalis ante alteram &amp;c.</hi> but the reaſon of this production is, becauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Ancients they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2017:10"/> with (ji) and ſo were long by poſition, which manner of writing, though it bee not now in vſe, yet the quantitie of the ſyllable ſtill remains.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe onely</hi> innuba, pronuba, <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds deriued of</hi> nubo; dejero, pejero, <hi>the compounds of</hi> juro, <hi>by compoſition change their long quantitie to ſhort?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: diuers other words alſo, as <hi>Omnipotens, Sacroſanctus, apud Buchan. Bardocucullus,</hi> Mart. <hi>integer, ab in, &amp; aeger: aeuiternus, ab aeuum, &amp; aeternus, nihilum, à ne, &amp; hilum:</hi> the ſecond ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lables of which are ſhort in compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, long out of compoſition: ſo <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidem, —ſiquidem ieiuna remanſit.</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. <hi>iubeo, à ius, &amp; habeo;</hi> whoſe firſt ſyllables become ſhort by compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that generally true: in</hi> t <hi>deſinentia breuia ſunt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: ſuch words are to be excepted which haue a conſonant before <hi>t,</hi> as <hi>amant, eſt, refert,</hi> and ſuch as are long by contraction, as,
<q>Nomen abît, aut vnde redît maiore triumpho. <bibl>
                        <hi>Lucan.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>If all nounes ending in <hi>e</hi> haue <hi>e</hi> ſhort
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2017:11"/> by quantitie, except the ablat. of the fifth declenſion, how is it that wee finde <hi>e</hi> in <hi>fame</hi> long in <hi>Virg.</hi> a noune of the third declenſion, as,</p>
               <p>Amiſſis (vt fama) apibus morbo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> fame<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>.</p>
               <p>It is not ſo made by <hi>Caeſura,</hi> becauſe it is not a ſyllable produced after a foot full and compleat falling any of the kinds of <hi>Caeſura</hi> in Grammar ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, we muſt therefore ſay that an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently <hi>(fames)</hi> was of the fift declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but now vſed onely in the third, yet here retaines the ſame quantitie which it had in former times, when it was of the fift.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that true which</hi> Lilly <hi>hath:</hi> Pes vna cum compoſitis, vt praepes, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes <hi>&amp;c?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: <hi>Praepes</hi> ſignifieth ſwift, not on foot, but in flying, it is not compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>prae,</hi> and <hi>pes,</hi> but deriued rather of <hi>praepeto,</hi> to haſten to with ſpeed: it is commonly vſed in the Poets, as an epithite of the Eagle, which is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to <hi>Icue, Praepes adunca Iouis, Ouid.</hi> In <hi>Tully, praepes auis,</hi> is the bird that firſt ſheweth himſelfe to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gur,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2017:11"/> whereby hee declares things to come: it may appeare by analogie very euidently, that <hi>praepes</hi> is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of <hi>pes: bipes</hi> makes <hi>bipedis, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drupes quadrupedis</hi> in the genit. caſe, but <hi>praepes praepetis,</hi> not <hi>praepedis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that rule of</hi> Lilly <hi>true,</hi> Longae ſunt omnes voces quartae inflexionis in <hi>us</hi> praeter <hi>nom. &amp; voc. ſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for the dat. and ablat. plurall in <hi>us,</hi> of all words of the fourth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion are ſhort, as well as the nom. and voc. ſingular.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of ETYMOLOGIE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHat is the meaning of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of Etymologie in</hi> Lilly. Etym. <hi>eſt ratio cognoſcendi caſuum diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimina?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meaning of it is this: that in Etymologie is handled the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of terminations of Nounes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounes, and Participles, by declining of Verbes by their coniugating from their firſt themes: as for example, the variations of <hi>Muſa</hi> in the oblique Caſes, are called <hi>Caſuum diſcrimina:</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2017:12"/> ſo likewiſe the differences of endings of <hi>doctus,</hi> whether it be varied by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining as <hi>doctus, a, um;</hi> or by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, as <hi>doctus, ior, iſſimus,</hi> are called <hi>caſuum diſcrimina. Caſus</hi> here is not to bee taken in ſo ſtrict an acception as it is afterwards, where it is ſaid, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſunt ſex,</hi> for it is attributed to a verbe alſo, for the variation of the verbe <hi>Amo</hi> in all Tenſes, Perſons, and Moodes, from its ſimple ſelfe are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this definition, <hi>Caſuum diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina.</hi> But yet mee thinkes the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is too narrow, though wee doe ſtretch the words after this manner, and comprehendeth vnder it onely the declineable parts of ſpeech, for though almoſt all aduerbs deriued from adjectiues be compared, and ſo bee varied in termination (yet they haue this nature as deriued rather then as aduerbs) and ſome few pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as <hi>ſupra, ſuperior, &amp;c.</hi> yet not any conjunction, or interjection admitteth of <hi>Caſuum diſcrimina,</hi> and very hardly any aduerbe which is ſo primitiuely, and originally.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2017:12"/>
               <head>Of the parts of Speech. Of a Noune.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>How are there eight parts of ſpeech, ſince a Pronoune, and a Participle haue the ſame things which belong to a Noune, to wit, Number, Caſe, Gender, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Pronoune, &amp; a Participle agree, and communicate with a Noune in theſe, but yet they haue ſeuerall and peculiar differences by which they are diſtinguiſhed, and conſtitute ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall parts of ſpeech: a Pronoune is diſtinguiſhed from a Noune by diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Perſon, and from a Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple by Time, and ſignification.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why doe you ſay that a Noune admits not difference of perſons: when as</hi> Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>in the nominatiue caſe is of the third perſon, in the vocatiue of the ſecond per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, according to that rule. The ſecond perſon is ſpoken to, as,</hi> Tu, Thou, <hi>and of this perſon is euery vocatiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A vocatiue caſe is ſaid to be of the ſecond perſon, not becauſe it is ſo of its proper ſignification, but by reaſon of the pronoune, <hi>Tu,</hi> with which it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2017:13"/> doth agree in the ſame caſe by appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This anſwere is giuen by ſome to make</hi> Lillies <hi>definition of a noune good, but in the definitions of</hi> Friſchline, Melanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon, Scaliger, <hi>and</hi> Finkius, <hi>there is no want of difference of Perſon mentioned to difference it from other parts of ſpeech.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true: The ſtreame of beſt Grammarians run, that a noune hath <hi>Perſons,</hi> but thus is diſtinguiſhed from a <hi>Pronoune,</hi> which ſignifies a thing with difference of Perſon as well as a Noune: a Noune ſignifies firſt, a Thing; ſecondarily, a Perſon: a Pronoune, firſt a Perſon; ſeconda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, a Thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If all Aduerbs, Coniunctions, &amp;c. be parts indeclinable, how comes it to paſſe that ſome of them are the Nominatiue Caſes to their Verbes, and haue Adie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues ioyned to them, agreeing with them in caſe, gender, &amp; number, as in</hi> Martial: Dic mihi cras iſtud Poſthume quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do venit: <hi>and againe,</hi> Magnum ſemper inane ſoph<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>s: <hi>or thus,</hi> Et eſt coniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio, Penes eſt praepoſitio. Vah eſt interjectio.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2017:13"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cras,</hi> and <hi>Soph<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and the other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles before the verbe <hi>eſt,</hi> are not nounes, but as it were nounes inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they ſupply the place of a nomin. caſe before the verbe, they are not properly nounes, but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, artificially as <hi>Melanchthon</hi> ſpeaketh: and in the ſame manner are verbes ſometimes vſed.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Matutinum portat ineptus <hi>ave.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Mart.</bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Quis expediuit Pſittico <hi>ſuum</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Per.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Scire tuum</hi> nihil eſt. <hi>Idem.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe not the nounes,</hi> Hora, Dies, Menſis, Annus, <hi>ſignifie difference of Time, as well as a participle; doth not the Time of an Houre differ from the Time of a Day, and the ſpace of a Moneth from the ſpace of an Yeere? how is it then that</hi> Lilly <hi>ſaith, a noune doth not ſignifie difference of Time?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true indeed, that theſe nounes conſidered co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paratiuely among them ſelues, doe ſignifie Times which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer among themſelues, but conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red abſolutely, and each by it ſelfe, they doe barely ſignifie a ſpace of Time, not conſignifie Time beſides its prime ſignification, as a participle
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2017:14"/> doth; as <hi>amans</hi> doth not onely ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the action (or rather paſſion) of louing, but conſignifies the preſent time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not ſome ſubſtantiues varied by three terminations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: we reade <hi>Syngraphus, Syngra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha, Syngraphum: Intybus, Intyba, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tybum: Vesper, &amp; vesperus, ra, rum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How doth that definition of a noune ſubſtantiue proper, hold:</hi> Quod vni ſoli conuenit; <hi>when as we reade many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per names in the plurall number?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The definition is true notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that exception: for a proper name in its owne nature is attributed but to one in the ſame <hi>ſpecies,</hi> but by accident to many. Firſt, when the ſame name agrees to many men: as, <hi>Virgilij, Simones, Scipiones.</hi> Secondly, when a noune metaphorically noteth a propertie or ſimilitude: as, <hi>Catones,</hi> for Wiſe-men. Thirdly, when the names of Nations, or Families, take vpon them the nature of appellatiues, as the <hi>Latini</hi> from <hi>Latinus, Fabij</hi> from <hi>Fabius,</hi> the Authors and Founders of that Nation, this Familie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2017:14"/>
               <head>Of the Accidents of a Noune. Of Species.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>When is a word ſaid to be of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue ſpecies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A word is ſaid to be of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſpecies, which is as the ſtemme, or roote, whence other wordes as branches doe ſprout forth; or as the fountaine, whence other words as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volets doe iſſue and flow forth, which are therefore called deriuatiues, as the noune of the primitiue ſpecies is <hi>nauis,</hi> of the deriuatiue ſpecies, are, <hi>nauigo, nauicula.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is ſpecies taken properly in Grammar, or metaphorically?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Metaphorically: ſpecies properly ſignifies an image, picture, or reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of any thing: the reaſon of borrowing this word, is this: as the image which repreſents it ſelfe to the eye of the body by a direct ray, is the prime image; that which is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by a reflected ray is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond image begot of the firſt: ſo that word which repreſents it ſelfe to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2017:15"/> the Vnderſtanding (which is the Eye of the Soule in its prime eſtate, is a word of the primitiue ſpecies, that which iſſues from the former of the deriuatiue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is a noune collectiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A noune which collecteth, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and vniteth a companie, or mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, in the ſingular number: as, <hi>Exercitus,</hi> an Armie; <hi>Grex,</hi> A flocke of ſheepe; <hi>Examen,</hi> A ſwarme of Bees.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi> Quis <hi>bee ſometimes a noune inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue, ſometimes a noune indefinite; how comes it to paſſe that</hi> Lillie <hi>claps it in amongst the pronounes afterwards, and ſubioynes to the rules of pronounes a catalogue of the compounds of</hi> Quis?</p>
               <p>It ſeemes to bee placed out of due order; vnleſſe peraduenture it viſite the pronounes by reaſon of ſome ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming affinitie it hath with <hi>Qui.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It is ſaid in the Engliſh Rudiments, that</hi> Quid <hi>is alwayes a ſubſtantiue of the neuter gender, is that true?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: <hi>Quid</hi> is not a ſubſtantiue, but is put ſometimes ſubſtantiuely with a genitiue caſe: as, <hi>Quid noui?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2017:15"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not</hi> Quid <hi>ſometimes vſed for</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnum?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <l>Neſcio, quid certe eſt, &amp; Hylax in limine latrat. <bibl>
                           <hi>Virg.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </l>
                  </q> 
                  <q>
                     <l>Neſcio, quid certè eſt, quod me tibi temperat aſtrum. <bibl>
                           <hi>Perſ.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>So among the Greekes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vſed for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Plat. in ap. Socr.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why are</hi> Vnus, Duo, Tres, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuor, &amp;c. <hi>the firſt kindes of numerall nounes of the primitiue ſpecies, called Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe the digit numbers are the firſt and chiefe numbers, vpon the which the reſt doe depend, and turne as the doore vpon the hinges, which in latine are called <hi>cardines,</hi> the reſt being but reſumptions of them. So the foure great and chiefe windes, are called the Cardinall windes, and the chiefe, and mayne point in any buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is called, <hi>Cardo cauſae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whence is a noune Patronymicke de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the Greeke words, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Father; and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Name; which hath its name from the father. So it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2017:16"/> onely ſignifies, being ſtrictly taken according to the <hi>Etymon.</hi> as <hi>Tydides,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Tydeus; Pelides,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Peleus;</hi> but yet it is vſed in a larger extent, to ſignifie many other relations by marriage, as <hi>Aeacides,</hi> the ſonne, or nephew of <hi>Aeacus; Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi> the daughter or neece of <hi>Nereus; Menelais,</hi> the wife of <hi>Menelaus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Figure.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe Grammarians meane when they aske that queſtion:</hi> Cuius eſt figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae eſt hoc nomen?</p>
               <p>They aske whether it bee a ſimple noune, as <hi>parabilis,</hi> or a compound as <hi>reparabilis,</hi> or a decompound as <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parabilis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth not compoſition ſometimes change gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is of the maſcul. gen. but <hi>atomus</hi> the compound is of the femin. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is of the maſcu. gender, but <hi>diphthongus</hi> is of the femin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are there not diuers words which are vſed by latine Authors, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of greeke and latine words, and latine and greeke words?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2017:16"/>
               <p>Yes: theſe are compounded of greeke, and latine words:
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Monoculus,</hi> for which ſome had rather ſay <hi>Vnoculus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bigamus,</hi> for which ſome had rather ſay <hi>Digamus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorus,</hi> for which ſome had rather ſay <hi>Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phagus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Archigubernus, Protonotarius, Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dux, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe of latine, and greeke words:<note n="*" place="margin">Of this ranke <hi>Cooper</hi> in his Dictionarie makes <hi>Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capnus,</hi> which hee engliſheth moſt ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, One that ſitteth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in the ſmoake, or by the fire, as it were a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of <hi>homo</hi> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: wheras indeed it is wholly a greeke word, and ſignifies, One that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyes the ſame fire, or ſmoake with another, an epithite gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to a wife by <hi>Arist. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Polit.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Prologus,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they make the firſt ſyllable long; <hi>Epitogium, Elogium, Grauitona, Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diameter, Biſſyllabum, Imbuo, ab in, &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Induo, ab in, &amp;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> vide <hi>Rod. Boclen. prob. Gram. l.</hi> 3. 29. <hi>p.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Number.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that rule true concerning all nounes; the ſingular number ſpeaketh of one, the plurall of more then one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: ſome nounes are ſingular by poſition, or termination, but plurall in ſenſe and vnderſtanding, as <hi>Turba, concie, exercitus, &amp;c.</hi> Againe, ſome nounes are plurall by poſition, and ſingular in ſenſe: as, <hi>Athenae, lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2017:17"/>
               <head>Of Caſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it neceſſarie to make a ſeuenth or eighth Caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: the ſeuenth which Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians make by an ablatiue caſe with a prepoſition, is altogether ſuperfluous, for no prepoſition enters into the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a caſe, ſo likewiſe is their eighth caſe, for it is the datiue put for the accuſatiue, with the prepoſition <hi>ad:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In <hi>coelum</hi> is not a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation.</note> as, <hi>It clamor coelo.</hi> i. <hi>ad coelum.</hi> Virg. <hi>Quaerere ſibi adiumenta honoribus.</hi> i. <hi>ad honores conſequendos.</hi> Cic.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why is the Ablatiue called</hi> Latinus Caſus?</p>
               <p>Becauſe it is proper to the Latines; the Greeks altogether want it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How then is it that we finde in</hi> Tully lat. <hi>prepoſitions which gouerne onely an ablatiue caſe, conſtrued with greeke nounes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true, there is ſuch <hi>ſyntaxe</hi> found in <hi>Tully,</hi> as 13. <hi>Ep. ad Att. Id ab</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>eſt remotiſſimum:</hi> and elſewhere. <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia cum</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: where the words <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, though they be the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2017:17"/> datiue caſe, take vpon them the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the ablatiue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Gender.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth not the feminine gender ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times imply the maſculine, as well as the maſculine the feminine?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes; hereof are diuers examples in Authors. <hi>Plaut. in Cistell. Scen. Niſi quid. Eam (rem) vult ſuae matri, &amp; patri, &amp;c. vbi (ſuae) innuit (ſuo)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Curtius</hi> is called <hi>Fama</hi> by <hi>Virg. in Culice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hic &amp; Fama vetus nunquam moritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra per aeuum.</hi> Curtius.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Maiestas veſtra,</hi> is the ordinarie title of a King.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poteſtas,</hi> doth ſignifie Magiſtrates, and Iudges: <hi>Fenest. c.</hi> 26. <hi>De Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratore Caeſaris, caeteriſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Romanis pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatibus.</hi> Sueton. in Claud. Caeſ. <hi>Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictionem de fidei-commiſſis quotannis, &amp; tantum in vrbe delegari magiſtratibus ſolitam in perpetuum, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> etiam per pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincias potestatibus demandauit.</hi> So Saint <hi>Paul</hi> Rom. 13.1. vſeth <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which <hi>Beza</hi> renders, <hi>pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates ſupereminentes,</hi> to ſignifie Kings:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2017:18"/> ſo <hi>Nobilitaes,</hi> is in <hi>Lucan</hi> put for the Nobilitie, or Peeres of a Land. <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas cum plebe perit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are all names of Males of the maſc. gender, of Females of the feminine; and all nounes that ſignifie both ſexes of both genders?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: ſometimes one and the ſame gender doth agree to both ſexes, as is apparant in the names of birds, fiſhes, and other creatures, whoſe ſexe is not ſet forth by ſeuerall wordes: as in <hi>Paſſer, Aquila, Oſtreum.</hi> So <hi>Liberi,</hi> though it bee onely of the maſculine gender, is put both for ſonnes and daughters, and <hi>mancipium</hi> of the neut. gender, onely ſignifies a bond-man, or a bond-woman, a Hee, or a Shee captiue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that a proper ſpeech which is ſet downe in the Engliſh Rudiments:</hi> the maſculine gender is declined with this article, <hi>Hic?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it is very harſh and inſolent; no gender, being the accident of a noune, can bee ſaid to bee declined; but euery noune which is declinable is declared to bee of the maſculine gender,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2017:18"/> hauing the article <hi>Hic</hi> prefixed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why are articles vſed in Grammar?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not to point out an <hi>indiuidium,</hi> or particular Thing, or Perſon, nor to diſtinguiſh ſexe, for Grammar conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders not the natures of things, but the names onely, as <hi>Lilly</hi> himſelfe confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, but to difference one gender from another: an article doth not make a noune of ſuch, or ſuch a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but demonſtrates it to be ſo: it is not the cauſe of the gender, but the ſigne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> Propria quae maribus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that marginall note true, which the Poſer of the</hi> Accidence <hi>hath in his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent vpon the first generall rule touching proper names,</hi> viz. Cocytus, <hi>the name of a Fenne in hell, is of the fem. gender.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: I finde it of the maſc. gender in the moſt refined Authors:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Viſendus ater flumine languido Cocy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> Hor. 2. Car.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Inamaenum forte ſedebat Cocytum iuxta.</hi> Stat. 1. Theb.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that exception of</hi> Stockwood <hi>to the ſecond generall rule of proper names,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2017:19"/> good,</hi> viz. <hi>that</hi> Epidaurus, <hi>the name of a Citie is of the maſc. gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for I finde it of the fem. gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in <hi>Martial. Aereis imposta iugis, medicam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Epidaurum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How are the proper noune,</hi> Opus, <hi>a Citie, and the appellatiue,</hi> Opus, <hi>a worke, distinguiſhed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By their genitiue caſes: <hi>Opus,</hi> the noune proper maketh <hi>Opuntis: Opus,</hi> the appellatiue, <hi>Operis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is contayned in the firſt generall rule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much: Theſe all are maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines: the names of Gods, the names of Men, of Moneths, of Windes, of Floods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are none to be excepted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: <hi>Styx,</hi> and <hi>Lethe,</hi> which are ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of hell, found in the Poets of the femin. gen. —<hi>Styx inde nouem circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flua campo.</hi> Stat. —<hi>ſoporiferae bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berem ſi pocula Lethes.</hi> Ouid. we need not excuſe <hi>Lilly,</hi> by ſaying they are Fennes, not Riuers. So <hi>Albula</hi> of the fem. gen. as, <hi>Albula pota Deo,</hi> where we neede not force a Syncheris; the rule muſt be ſquared to the examples,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2017:19"/> not the examples to the rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is contayned in the ſecond gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much: the names of women, Earthly and Diuine, of Regions, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Iles, are feminine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are none to be excepted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: beſides thoſe which are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, theſe, <hi>Londinum, Eboracum, Brunduſium, Pergamon,</hi> are of the neut. gen. <hi>as</hi> Virg. <hi>Miramur Troiae cineres, &amp; flebile victis Pergamon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the generall rules of Appellatiues.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi> ſuber, <hi>and</hi> ſiler <hi>be rightly placed in</hi> appellatiua arborum &amp;c. <hi>how is it that wee finde them againe in the ſecond exception of neuters, from the third ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall rule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot excuſe <hi>Lilly</hi> herein, it is a vaine exception, or Tautologie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Epicens.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>May not the rule,</hi> ſunt etiam volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum &amp;c. <hi>be ſpared?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, as I conceiue: for firſt, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2017:20"/> not to a Grammarian, but to a Philoſopher, to conſider the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of ſexes. Secondly, the genders of the names of birds, wilde beaſts, and fiſhes, are to bee knowne by the rules following. Thirdly, if this rule ſhew the gender of thoſe nounes in the ſame ſpecified, how is that wee finde the genders of them ſet downe againe: of birds, as <hi>Halcyon, Bubo, Perdix, Phoenix, Nycticorax:</hi> of beaſts, as <hi>Elephas, Linx:</hi> of fiſh, as <hi>Halec.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If all nounes appellatiue ending in</hi> um, <hi>be of the neuter gender, according to that rule,</hi> Omne quod exit in <hi>um. why doth</hi> Lilly <hi>ſay againe in the ſecond exception from the firſt ſpeciall rule,</hi> Et quot in <hi>on</hi> vel in <hi>um.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thinke that part touching nounes ending in <hi>um,</hi> might be ſpared, and the rule better thus contracted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neutrum nomen in</hi> e, <hi>ſi gignit</hi> Is <hi>vt mare, rete.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et quot in</hi> on, ſea <hi>Barbiton. Et pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus, lacoethes,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hippomanes, virus. Neutrum modo, mas modo vulgus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the meaning of</hi> Inuariabile nomen?</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2017:20"/>
               <p>Not only <hi>euery ſubſtantiue vndeclined,</hi> as the Poſer of the <hi>Accidence</hi> ſpeaks: but alſo all <hi>nomina</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>viz.</hi> all clauſes which are the nominatiue caſe to the verbe, as in that clauſe, <hi>didiciſſe fideliter artes Emollit mores; didiciſſe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliter artes</hi> muſt be conceiued to be of the neuter gender, as alſo all verbs of the infinitiue moode vſed ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely, whether they come before their verbe, or follow after; as, <hi>Velle ſuum cui<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> est.</hi> Perſ. <hi>Videamus beate</hi> viuere veſtrum <hi>quale ſit.</hi> Cicer. <hi>Plaut. in Curc. ſc.</hi> 1. <hi>Ita</hi> tuum <hi>conferto</hi> amare <hi>ſemper ſi ſapis. Ne id quod ames, popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus ſi ſciat, tibi ſit probro.</hi> Idem in Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chid. ſc. Iamdudum. <hi>Hic</hi> vereri <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didit</hi> i, e, <hi>verecundiam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe you thinke of that which is annexed to the firſt ſpeciall rule,</hi> Labes, labis. Peſtes, peſtis.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peſtes</hi> is here ſet downe by <hi>Lilly</hi> (or I know not who) as the nomin. caſe, which word is not found in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pure Author, nor in any Lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con: and it ſeemes rather to bee an error of the Compoſer then a ſlip of the Printer, inaſmuch as hee would
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2017:21"/> haue <hi>pictis</hi> by analogie, the gen. caſe of <hi>pestes,</hi> as <hi>labis</hi> of <hi>labes;</hi> this hath paſſed in all editions that I haue ſeene without correction: the true nomin. caſe is <hi>pestis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> Lilly <hi>ſpeake properly, when hee ſaith,</hi> Scriba, Aſſecla, Lixa, &amp;c. <hi>are the names of men?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for in proprietie of ſpeech they are not the names of men, but of the offices, or imployments of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that generally true,</hi> Maſcula grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum quot declinatio prima fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>No: for as learned <hi>Ramus</hi> obſerues in his Grammar, there be many words borrowed of the Greeks by the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, which being of the maſculine gender and firſt declenſion, of the Greeks are of the feminine gender in latine Authors; which I haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized in this Diſtich:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Foeminei generis ſunt haec Graecani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</hi> Charta, Gauſapa, Margarita, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarracta, <hi>&amp;</hi> Catapulta.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are</hi> funis, <hi>and</hi> ſentis <hi>of the maſcul. gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ramus,</hi> and <hi>Stephanus</hi> ſay, they are
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2017:21"/> of the Common of two: ſo alſo <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell. in Prompt. Sentis com. g. teſte Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca. aſprae ſentes.</hi> Virg. Aeneid. 2. <hi>Funis tam maſc. quam foem. teste</hi> Gellio lib. 13. <hi>citante verſ. Lucret.</hi> Aurea de coelo demiſit funis in arua.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> rete <hi>alwayes of the neuter gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We reade both <hi>retis,</hi> and <hi>rete, rete</hi> is alwayes of the neuter gen. <hi>retis</hi> of the maſc. <hi>Varro.</hi> this is a noune re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant: as alſo, <hi>Barbiton,</hi> for wee reade in <hi>Horace, Barbitus,</hi> of the fem. gender. <hi>Age dic Latinum Barbite car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Carm. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ode</hi> 32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is Halcyonis of the doubtfull gender, as</hi> Lilly <hi>beares vs in hand?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: in this word <hi>Lilly</hi> was foulely deceiued, and by this hath deceiued others. Firſt, he was deceiued in that hee tooke for a word which did not encreaſe in the gen. caſe, where as it is in true the genitiue caſe of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatiue, <hi>Halcyon,</hi> a King-fiſher, ſo called, becauſe ſhee buildeth her neſt in the Sea, and there hatcheth her yong. Secondly, in that he ſaith it is of the doubtfull gender, where it is alwayes found with a femin. epithite.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2017:22"/> as <hi>Vir. Dilectae Thetidi Halcyones.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Nunc ego deſertas alloquar Halcyonas. <hi>Proper.</hi> Maeſtae.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Halcyones lugubre dabant per littora car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. <bibl>
                        <hi>Mant.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <p>Secondly, hee deceiued others, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them the Conſtruer of <hi>Lillies</hi> Rules, who ſwallowed downe this flie, putting <hi>Halcyonis</hi> for a King-fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher, and other ordinarie Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters following him, are deceiued alſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> ficus <hi>for a diſeaſe, of the doubtfull gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No:<note n="*" place="margin">Màrtial E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pigr. l. <hi>1.</hi> Ep. <hi>66.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Martial</hi> who knew the gender of it better then <hi>Lilly,</hi> ſaith, it is of the<note n="a" place="margin">Sic quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam è plebe Grammaticis videtur: ego autem in Thomae Farnabij viri <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſententiam pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus eo; cuius verba in Notis ad hac Epigram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma operaepreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um erit recenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Cum nihil hic de genere moueatur, neque apud probae notae autorem quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam reperiatur ficus pro morbo in alio, quam foemineo genere, vt &amp; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Graeca exponunt è ſuos liberos fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulos, pueros delicatos.</note> maſc. gender.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Dicemus <hi>ficus,</hi> quas ſcimus in arbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re naſci</l>
                  <l>Dicemus <hi>ficos,</hi> Caeciliane, tuos.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the meaning of the ſecond ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall rule,</hi> Nomen creſcentis &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Poſer of the <hi>Accidence,</hi> ſaith, this is the meaning: that euery noune ſubſtantiue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, increaſing ſharpe, or long in the gen. caſe, that is, being lifted vp in pronouncing, or pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced long, is of the feminine gender.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:2017:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi> Lilly <hi>meane by</hi> ſyllaba acuta, <hi>a long ſyllable with an acute accent vpon it, then many of the words put in the rules of exception, are in vaine excepted, for many of them increaſe ſhort?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis very true: amongſt the maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines excepted, theſe encreaſe ſhort, <hi>Sal, ſalis. Vir, viri. Mas, maris. Pes, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis. Grex, gregis. Phryx, phrygis.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the doubtfull: <hi>Scrobs, ſcrobis. Grus, gruis.</hi> Amongſt the Common of two: <hi>Dux, ducis. Bos, bouis. Sus, ſuis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why doth</hi> Lilly <hi>ſay,</hi> Glis gliris ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens genitiuo.</p>
               <p>To diſtinguiſh it from <hi>Glis gliſſis,</hi> Potters clay, and <hi>Glis glitis,</hi> a Thiſtle, both which words are of the femi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine gender.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not that rule,</hi> Maſcula in er, or, &amp; os, <hi>faultie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, and it may bee thus compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly amended: <hi>Maſcula in er, or, &amp; os, ſeu Crater, conditor, heros;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In Dens, quale bidens: Torens, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frens, orienſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adde gigas, elephas, adam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tapeſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:2017:23"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>At<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Lebes, magnes, hydrops, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dranſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> meridi-</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Es. Phoenix, bombyx, thorax, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vex<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> corax<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sunt haec foeminea in</hi> n <hi>&amp;</hi> or, <hi>Syren, ſoror, vxor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why doe you turne out of this rule,</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res: Quae componuntur ab aſſe vt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drans, ſemis; &amp; Mulier?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cures</hi> is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue, as <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bij</hi> and <hi>Locri.</hi>
                  </note>Firſt: <hi>Cures</hi> is no noune appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, but a proper name of a towne of the Sabines; which is read onely in the plurall number. <hi>Tutio<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſeni, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſeueris.</hi> Virg. Secondly, <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drans,</hi> and <hi>Semis,</hi> are no compounds of <hi>As;</hi> firſt, <hi>Dodrans</hi> is no compound, as appeares by its ſignification, for it doth not ſignifie, <hi>nine pounds,</hi> which it ſhould if it were compounded of <hi>dodra</hi> and <hi>as,</hi> but nine ounces: as alſo by analogie; as of <hi>decem</hi> and <hi>as</hi> comes <hi>decuſſis,</hi> of <hi>centum</hi> and <hi>as, centuſſis;</hi> ſo by analogie of <hi>dodra</hi> and <hi>as,</hi> ſhould reſult <hi>dodraſſis,</hi> not <hi>dodrans:</hi> and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Lilly</hi> forgot what hee had written before in the firſt exception of the firſt ſpeciall rule, that <hi>ab aſſenata</hi> were maſculines, not encreaſing in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiue
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2017:23"/> caſe. Secondly, <hi>ſemis</hi> is not found in any pure Writer as a ſimple word; it is not the nom. caſe of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſis,</hi> but <hi>ſemiſſis</hi> is it ſelfe the nom. caſe, compounded of <hi>ſemi</hi> and <hi>as,</hi> which <hi>ſemi</hi> is alwayes found in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as <hi>Semianimis, ſemivivus, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micircularis, ſemipedalis. Semibouem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> virum, ſemivirum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> bouem.</hi> Ouid. and is deriued of the greek word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which being turned into latine, in ſtead of the <hi>aſper ſpiritus,</hi> doth prefixe <hi>ſ,</hi> as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſuper;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſylua.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>Mulier,</hi> though in moderne Poets it bee made to encreaſe long, yet in truth it doth increaſe ſhort, and ſo the beſt Criticks pronounce it: that it increaſeth ſhort may bee thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. Firſt, it is found, the laſt word in many verſes in <hi>Terence,</hi> which doe commonly end in an Iambicke foote. Secondly, it is found, in any place of <hi>Virgil</hi> or <hi>Ouids</hi> works in any oblique caſe, and it is more then probable, that a word of ſuch common vſe would not haue beene baulked by them, had not the three firſt ſyllables in the oblique caſes made a tribra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2017:24"/> of which their verſes are alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether vncapable. Thirdly, that <hi>Iam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick Scazon</hi> in <hi>Martial,</hi> where <hi>(erum)</hi> makes an <hi>Iambus:</hi> for a <hi>Scazon</hi> neuer admits of a <hi>ſpondaeus</hi> in the ſecond odde place, put all out of doubt. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>methyſtinaſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> mulierum vocat veſtes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> perdix <hi>of the doubtfull gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It can ſcarce bee found in any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the maſculine gender, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily of the femin. as <hi>Ouid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Garrula ramoſa proſpexit ab ilice perdix.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mart. <hi>Et picta perdix.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mant. <hi>Daedala perdix, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may that rule,</hi> Sunt commune parens, &amp;c. <hi>be bettered?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus: <hi>Communis generis ſunt haec infans adoleſcens,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dux, illex, haeres, exlex, autor<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Latro, cliens, cuſtos, bos, fur, ſus, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Sacerdos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why is</hi> Bifrons <hi>turned out?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe, though it bee ſometimes vſed ſubſtantiuely, yet indeed it is an adiectiue, an epithite of <hi>Ianus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:2017:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturnuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſenex, Iuni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> bifrontis imago.</hi> Virg.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> autor <hi>vſed onely concerning Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: ſomtimes concerning Things, as, <hi>Multi ingenio ſibi autore dignitatem pepererunt.</hi> Cic. <hi>Calor autor leuitatis. Cometa ſideris autoris ſui ſequitur natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram.</hi> Scal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> Presbyter, <hi>which is called in Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> Vox Eccleſiaſtica, <hi>a good word or no?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it hath beene vſed by modern writers, but is in truth a barbarous word: the true latine word is <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terus,</hi> borrowed of the greeke <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What feminines are excepted from the third ſpeciall rule?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ordo,</hi> though it make <hi>Dinis,</hi> is of the maſc. gen. becauſe it is not an <hi>hyper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſyllabon:</hi> and <hi>Macedo</hi> is of the maſc. gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, becauſe though it be an <hi>hyperdiſſyll.</hi> yet it makes <hi>donis,</hi> not <hi>dinis,</hi> in the genitiue caſe.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Do,</hi> vel <hi>Go, Nomina hyperdiſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba gignunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quae Dinis, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Ginis ſicut dulcedo, propago.</hi> To which theſe may more compleatly bee added:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virgo, grando, fides, compes, teges, arbor, amazon,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bacchar, hyems, mulier, ſyndon, gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, ſeges, icon.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:2017:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe you thinke of that rule,</hi> Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula <hi>in</hi> as, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> caſpis, caſſis, cuſpis.</p>
               <p>I thinke that therein <hi>Lilly</hi> was in part deceiued, for <hi>caſſis</hi> and <hi>cuſpis</hi> are originally latine words, not to bee found in any greeke Lexicographer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is euery word, ſignifying a thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out life, ending in</hi> a, <hi>of the neuter gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, if it encreaſe ſhort in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiue caſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is then that many Grammarians haue affirmed, that</hi> polenta, <hi>though it encreaſe not at all in the genitiue caſe, is of the neuter gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is true, <hi>Alexander, Sulpitius, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briſſenſis, Baptiſta Pius,</hi> and <hi>Calepine,</hi> affirme ſo; and <hi>Mantuan</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the Grammarians of his time, did vſe it ſo, ſaying: <hi>Montibus artocreas, &amp; pingue polenta comedi.</hi> But in <hi>Apuleius</hi> wee finde, <hi>polentae caſeatae offula.</hi> In Varro, <hi>Obijciunt his polentam hordeaceam:</hi> the error aroſe firſt from the miſſe-conſtruction of that verſe in <hi>Ouids Metam. Dulce dedit testa, quod coxerat ante polenta:</hi> they cooſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a <hi>comma</hi> after <hi>ante,</hi> put in by
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2017:25"/> the non-intelligent Printer, thought <hi>polenta</hi> the accuſatiue, which was the ablatiue, as if the Poet had meant, <hi>dedit dulce polenta:</hi> which if it bee ſearcht into will be found non-ſenſe, for <hi>polenta</hi> ſignifieth dried barly, with which beere is brewed, but is not of it ſelfe any liquid thing which may bee drunke: the verſe is thus to bee conſtrued; <hi>Dedit dulce</hi> .i. <hi>dulcem po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> Shee gaue to <hi>Ceres</hi> ſweet drinke, <hi>quod coxerat ante polenta,</hi> which before ſhee had boyled with dried barly. <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> takes <hi>dulce</hi> here in the neuter gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſubſtantiuely, as afterwards, <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quidum. Iuuenem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cum liquido mixta perfudit Diua polenta;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Raphae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Regium, Ouidij Interp. in <hi>5.</hi> Metam.</note> 
                  <hi>Ceres</hi> beſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the impudent boy which derided her, with the drie barly mingled with the liquor: ſo <hi>Niniuita.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi> verber <hi>be read,</hi> Robinſon <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts</hi> Lilly, <hi>affirming, that onely</hi> verbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, <hi>and</hi> verbere <hi>are read.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is no maruell though they diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, ſince in patching vp our Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar they did not conferre their notes together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> iter <hi>belong to the rule of neutrall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2017:26"/> words, excepted from the third ſpeciall rule, ſince it is declined</hi> iter itineris, <hi>whereas thoſe which encreaſe in the geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue caſe, are to exceede the nom. onely in one ſyllable, and not in two?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The genitiue caſe <hi>Itineris</hi> is of an old word <hi>Itiner,</hi> which is growne out of vſe, not of <hi>iter,</hi> which is ſucceeded in its roome.</p>
               <p>Pecus pecoris <hi>ſeemes to bee of the fem. gender, as well as</hi> pecus pecudis, <hi>by that verſe of Ouid.</hi> Hoc Pecus omne meum, multae ſtabulantur in antris. <hi>Multae,</hi> in this verſe, doth not agree with <hi>pecora,</hi> but <hi>pecudes</hi> vnderſtood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the meaning of</hi> Onyx cum prole?</p>
               <p>That <hi>onyx</hi> with the off-ſpring, or compound thereof, <hi>Sardonyx,</hi> is of the doubtfull gender.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it any where found in the feminine gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No where, alwayes in the maſc.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et crocino nares myrrhcus vngat o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyx.</hi> Propert.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In dextra candidus ardet onyx, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are</hi> Augur <hi>and</hi> Aruſpex <hi>vſed in the fem. gender, as well as in the maſc.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2017:26"/>
               <p>I doe not thinke any example can be ſhewed, where they are vſed in the feminine gender: the Romanes had a Colledge of Augurs, but wee neuer reade of any woman admitted fellow there. <hi>Plautus</hi> would not vſe <hi>Haru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpex</hi> for a Shee-diuiner, but <hi>Hara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> princeps <hi>alwayes a ſubſtantiue of the common of two, as it is in</hi> Lilly?</p>
               <p>I thinke that it is primarily a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiuely, yet vſed ſometime in the roome and place of an adiectiue, as in that verſe of <hi>Horace:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Principibus placuiſſe viris non vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma laus est.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the firſt declenſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe all nounes of the firſt declenſion, ending in</hi> a, <hi>make the genitiue in</hi> ae?</p>
               <p>No: for wee reade <hi>Paterfamilias, Materfamilias, Filius familias</hi> in the gen. euen in the beſt and pureſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: and in the Ancients, <hi>vias, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras:</hi> the genitiue of <hi>via, terra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why did they write ſo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In imitation of the Greekes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom all ſubſtantiues ending
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2017:27"/> in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and α with a vowell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it forme the genitiue caſe by <hi>as.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It ſeemes that ſome latine words end in</hi> am, <hi>as well as Hebrew in the nom. caſe. I reade in</hi> Plautus; Ego patriam te rogo quae ſit tua, <hi>where</hi> patriam <hi>ſeemes to be the nominatiue caſe: for if the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence bee conſtrued, the words muſt bee placed thus;</hi> Rogo te quae ſit patriam tua?</p>
               <p>The words cannot bee ſo placed: but here is an Antiptoſis, the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue put for the nominatiue, <hi>patriam</hi> for <hi>patria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If all nounes of the first declenſion in</hi> as, <hi>make the vocatiue in</hi> a, <hi>how is it that we reade in</hi> Terence, Pythias <hi>in the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiue caſe,</hi> Quid feſtinas, aut quem quaeris Pythias, <hi>in Eun. Act.</hi> 4. <hi>ſc.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>In this there is an Atticiſme: the Atticks in all declenſions make the vocatiue like the nominatiue, and yet we finde regularly in the ſame Scene; <hi>Paululum ſi ceſſaſſem Pythia, domi non offendiſſem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are</hi> à Muſa, à Magiſtro, <hi>ablatiue caſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vulgar Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marians confound
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2017:27"/> Syntaxis with Etymologie, when in declining a noune that ſay in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat. <hi>ab hac Muſa, ab hoc Magistro;</hi> this is conſtruction, not declining: if they will ſay, the prepoſition is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixed onely as a ſigne; I anſwere, that this ſigne is nor perpetuall; this appeares in <hi>Siquis, ecquis. Nequis, nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis:</hi> for none will ſay, <hi>à ſiquo, ab ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo, à nequo, à nunquo.</hi> Goclen. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem. Gram. l. 1. p. 24.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth not</hi> anima <hi>ſometimes make the datiue, and ablatiue caſes plurall in</hi> abus, <hi>as well as</hi> Dea liber<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yes, and ſometimes in <hi>is</hi> alſo: for we reade in <hi>Cicero. Tullius Terentiae, &amp; Pater Tulliolae duabus animis ſuis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem dicit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe not words of the firſt declenſion make the datiue and ablatiue caſes plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, regularly in</hi> is?</p>
               <p>Yes: but theſe which follow are to bee excepted, whereof ſome make <hi>is</hi> and <hi>abus,</hi> as nounes redundant; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>abus</hi> onely: which for the helpe of memorie I haue reduced into this diſtich:</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:2017:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Filia, nata, anima</hi> is <hi>faciunt, atque</hi> abus, <hi>at</hi> abus <hi>Tantùm, Ambae, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> duae, liberta, equa, ſic dea, mula.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the ſecond Declenſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many terminations bee there of the ſecond declenſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Eight: the examples of them I haue compiled in this Hexameter:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>TemplVM, annVS, vIR, apER, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tVR, OrphEVS, IliON, ArgOS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is there an imitation of the Attick dialect of the Greekes, which formes the vocatiue like to the nominatiue, in that verſe of Ouid.</hi> Latmius Endymion non eſt tibi luna rubori, <hi>as</hi> Lilly <hi>ſuppoſeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſee no reaſon for that ſuppoſall, for <hi>Latmius Endymion</hi> is the nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue caſe to the verbe <hi>est,</hi> not the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiue: the Poet according to the true originall copie, doth not direct his ſpeech to <hi>Endymion,</hi> but to the <hi>Moone:</hi> the meaning is, that <hi>Diana</hi> was not aſhamed to deſcend to the louing embracements of <hi>Endymion</hi> on the hill <hi>Latmus. Endymion</hi> was an Aſtronomer, and for the cleerer ſight
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2017:28"/> of the ſtarres, did often goe to the top of that mountaine, which gaue hint to the fable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What words bee thoſe of the ſecond declenſion, which make the vocatiue in</hi> e <hi>and in</hi> us?</p>
               <p>Theſe ſixe: which to helpe the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, I haue comprized in this verſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haec: vulgus, lucus, populus, fluuius, chorus, agnus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe not</hi> Quercus, <hi>and</hi> Laurus, <hi>forme the vocatiue in</hi> e, <hi>or</hi> us, <hi>as well as theſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes; but not in the ſame reſpect: for they forme the vocatiue in <hi>e,</hi> as of the ſecond declenſion: and in <hi>us,</hi> as of the fourth declenſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> vulgus <hi>make the vocatiue in</hi> e, <hi>and in</hi> us, <hi>as of the maſc. gender.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it hath that double terminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a double conſideration: as it makes <hi>e</hi> in the voc. it is of the maſc. gender, as <hi>us</hi> of the neuter: and here alſo may be noted, that the ending of the reſt of the nounes in <hi>us</hi> in the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiue caſe, is an Archaiſme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How doe greeke words in</hi> os, <hi>as</hi> Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos, <hi>make the vocatiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the latine words in <hi>us</hi> regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:2017:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the reaſon that</hi> Panthus, <hi>and</hi> Oedipus, <hi>make the vocatiue in</hi> u?</p>
               <p>Becauſe they come of greek words in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in the vocatiue, which is rendred in latine by <hi>u.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the third Declenſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>What nounes of the third declenſion make the accuſatiue caſe in</hi> im <hi>onely?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe; which for memories ſake may thus rime:
<q>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>im, rauim, ſitim, tuſſim,</l>
                     <l>Charybdim, maguderim, &amp; amuſſim.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What nounes make the accuſatiue both in</hi> im, <hi>and in</hi> em?</p>
               <p>Theſe:
<q>
                     <l>Im, Em. faciunt, febris, buris,</l>
                     <l>Peluis, puppis, &amp; ſecuris.</l>
                     <l>Torquis, turris, aqualis, nauis.</l>
                     <l>Et bipennis, reſtis, clauis.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the genitiue caſe of the third declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion end in</hi> is, <hi>how comes it to paſſe that wee reade</hi> duri miles Vlyſſi. Immitis Achilli?</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>Vlyſſi,</hi> which <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</hi> vſeth in the genitine caſe, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of his <hi>Aeneid.</hi> (and the ſame is to bee ſaid alſo of <hi>Achilli</hi>) wee muſt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2017:29"/> obſerue that it is of the third declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the contracts amongſt the Greekes, whoſe nom. ending in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and genit. in <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Vlyſſeus, Vlyſſeos;</hi> the ancient Grammarians were wont to diuide <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> into two ſyllables, whoſe genitiue they made <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo, as <hi>Vlyſsëus, Vlyſsëi;</hi> and the vowels ſo diuided, they did againe contract into the diphthong <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by Synecphoneſis, as <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> for <hi>Vlyſſei:</hi> and afterward by Synaereſis they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the diphthong by <hi>i,</hi> as <hi>Vlyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi</hi> for <hi>Vlyſſei.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe any nounes of the third declenſion decreaſe in the genitiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: thoſe that imagine that <hi>Iupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> makes <hi>Iouis</hi> in the genitiue caſe, are deceiued; and thoſe that decline it ſo, may as well ſay. Nom. <hi>Phoebus.</hi> Gen. <hi>Apollinis,</hi> ſaith the Grammarian. <hi>Probus Inſtitut. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Iupiter</hi> is a Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nymon of the ancient nominat. caſe: <hi>Iouis,</hi> which was declined <hi>Iouis</hi> in the genitiue caſe alſo, but now the nominatiue is out of vſe, and <hi>Iupiter</hi> vſed in ſtead of it; but the other caſes keepe their ancient forme.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:2017:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that rule of</hi> Lilly <hi>generally true, that Adiectiues, except thoſe which end in is, and</hi> en, <hi>and make</hi> e <hi>in the neuter gender, make the ablatiue both</hi> e <hi>and</hi> i?</p>
               <p>No: for adiectiues ending in <hi>ns,</hi> doe not make the ablatiue promiſcuouſly in <hi>e</hi> or <hi>i:</hi> in this we muſt be very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruant of the vſe of authors, we may ſay, <hi>me perlubente, me imprudente;</hi> but we may not ſay, <hi>me perlubenti, me im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudenti:</hi> neither may we ſay <hi>gauden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, libenti, patienti, abſenti illo factum eſt:</hi> for the ablatiue of the participle of the preſent tenſe, being ioyned with another word put abſolutely, ends onely in <hi>e:</hi> yet wee may ſay in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of conſtruction, <hi>animo Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denti, patienti, laetanti faciam. Goclen. probl. gram. l.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that rule of</hi> Lillie <hi>generally true.</hi> Comparatiua bifariam facient ablati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum in <hi>e</hi> vel <hi>i?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: the comparatiues of the foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine gender doe moſt commonly make the ablatiue in <hi>e,</hi> as <hi>laetiore fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, ſecundiore fortuna, vocis contentione maiore, grauitate acriore, commodiore valetudine, longiore via.</hi> Comparatiues
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2017:30"/> of the neuter gender moſt commonly make the ablatiue in <hi>i,</hi> as <hi>a Marori, a Pari, a fortiori; ardentiori ſtudio, Cic.</hi> vide <hi>Goclen. ibid.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the fourth Declenſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>What words of the fourth declenſion make the datiue, and the ablatiue caſes plural in</hi> ubus.</p>
               <p>Theſe comprehended in this diſtich for memory ſake.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Haec in <hi>vbus,</hi> ficus, portus,</l>
                  <l>partus, ſpecus, arcus</l>
                  <l>Sic lacus, atque veru, ſic</l>
                  <l>quercus, acus, tribus, artus.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the fift Declenſion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> plebes, plebei <hi>to be vſed by any one that would write purely?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it was a word anciently vſed, but now is exolete: if <hi>plebs</hi> be a noune redundant, as <hi>Robinſon</hi> ſaith, then <hi>ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes</hi> muſt be the other nominatiue caſe; not <hi>plebis,</hi> as he ſaith in his rules of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teroclits: <hi>plebis</hi> is no where found but in the genitiue of <hi>plebs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:2017:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> Quaegenus, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe you thinke of that rule,</hi> Haec genus, ac partim flexum variantia, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I thinke it might very well haue beene ſpared. <hi>Pergama</hi> ſeemes to be the plurall of <hi>Pergamon,</hi> found in <hi>Virg.</hi> rather then of <hi>Pergamus.</hi> Some ſay that <hi>ſupellectilia</hi> is the plural of <hi>ſupellex,</hi> but is ſcarce to be found in any pure author: it fell not within the verge of the reading of the compoſer of theſe rules, and therefore hee ſaith, <q>Quod niſi plurali careut &amp;c.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are nounes aptote?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not ſuch as haue no caſes, but ſuch as doe not admit of difference of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations in oblique caſes, they are deriued of α, a priuatiue particle, and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>cado.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are</hi> cornu <hi>and</hi> genu <hi>ſuch?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet we reade that theſe haue other ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, as</hi> cornuum, cornibus, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuum, genibus.</p>
               <p>The rule is to be vnderſtood of theſe in the ſingular, not in the plurall number.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:2017:31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>What part of ſpeech is fas?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A noune adiectiue, vſed onely in the neuter gender; and of the ſame na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is <hi>nefas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi> Inſtar <hi>be a noune, as</hi> Robinſon <hi>ſaith, how comes it to paſſe that in the ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxis of aduerbs we finde this rule,</hi> Inſtar aequiparationem, menſuram &amp;c. ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficat, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>It is an euident contradiction, and no maruell, ſince our Grammer is a <hi>Cento</hi> made vp of the ſhreds of ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not the rule touching</hi> Triptots <hi>faultie?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: firſt in that hee ſaith, <hi>frugis,</hi> and <hi>ditionis</hi> want their nominatiue caſes, whereas <hi>fruges,</hi> and <hi>ditio</hi> are found in good authors, and are not ſcrupulouſly to be refuſed. Secondly, in that he ſaith <hi>opis,</hi> hath the plurall number compleate and perfect: it is true, <hi>opes</hi> is read in all caſes in the plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall number, but it hath not any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to <hi>opis,</hi> but is a fcminine plurall, wanting the ſingular number, and is to be referred to that rule, <hi>Haec ſunt fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minei generis, numerique ſecundi, &amp;c.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2017:32"/> the ſignifications of <hi>opis:</hi> &amp; <hi>opes,</hi> though they haue ſome kinred, yet they differ much; <hi>opis,</hi> helpe, <hi>opes,</hi> riches. If he will ſay that <hi>opis</hi> hath the plurall number, hee may as well ſay that <hi>delicium</hi> hath the plurall number alſo, for <hi>deliciae</hi> is euery where read: and that <hi>Tricae, apinae, plugae,</hi> hath the ſingular number, for <hi>trica, apina, pluga</hi> are found frequently in the ſingular number in different ſignification.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> omnis <hi>want the vocatiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: we read in the Poet, <hi>Dijque Deae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> omnes.</hi> O all ye Gods and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haue no Pronounes the vocatiue caſe,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>but onely</hi> noſter, noſtras, meus &amp; tu?</p>
               <p>Yes: <hi>Ipſe</hi> hath the vocatiue caſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; as in the Poet,
<q>Ipſe meas aether ſuſcipe ſumme preces.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may</hi> Robinſons <hi>rule be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus: <hi>Et Pronomina, praeter</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quinque notanda. Meus, tu, nostras, noster, &amp; ipſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What Nounes want the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:2017:32"/>
               <p>All, or the moſt part that for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie ſake are compriſed in this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtich.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Propria,</hi> 2. <hi>Virtutes,</hi> 3. <hi>Artes,</hi> 4. <hi>Penſa,</hi> 5. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>da,</hi> 6. <hi>Figura.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Morbi,</hi> 8. <hi>Herbae,</hi> 9. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itia,</hi> 10. <hi>Aetates,</hi> 11. <hi>Frumenta,</hi> 12. <hi>Metella.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. As <hi>Thomas, Richardus.</hi> 2. <hi>Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, Iustitia.</hi> 3. <hi>Grammatica Logica.</hi> 4. <hi>Piper, Saccharum.</hi> 5. <hi>Aromatices.</hi> 6. <hi>Synecdoche, Metaphora.</hi> 7. <hi>Podagra, Cephalalgia.</hi> 8. <hi>Amaranthus, Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racus.</hi> 9. <hi>Deſidia, Auaritia.</hi> 10. <hi>Iuuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, Senecta.</hi> 11. <hi>triticum.</hi> 12. <hi>aurum ferrum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not</hi> ſanguis <hi>read in the plurall number?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, in eccleſiaſticall writers, but then the word is forced to expreſſe an Hebraiſme, as, <hi>vir ſanguinum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lilly <hi>ſaith that</hi> nemo <hi>is of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of two,</hi> Robinſon <hi>that it is of the maſculine gender; what doe you thinke of their variance?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phocas,</hi> and other Grammarians ſide with <hi>Robinſon,</hi> and they adde, that <hi>Homo</hi> alſo is of the maſculine gender,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2017:33"/> of which <hi>nemo</hi> is a compound. Neither of theſe nounes are found with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectiue of the feminine gender: it is true that <hi>Terence</hi> hath in his <hi>Andria, Scio neminem peperiſſe hic:</hi> and <hi>Virg. nec vox hominem ſonat,</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Venus:</hi> and <hi>Sulpicius</hi> in an Epiſtle to <hi>Cicero,</hi> (wherein hee comforts him for the death of his daughter <hi>Tullia</hi>) hath theſe words, <hi>Quae ſi iam diem ſuum non obijſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet paulo poſt tam ei moriendu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuit, quam homo nata erat:</hi> where <hi>nata</hi> doth not agree with <hi>homo,</hi> but <hi>Tullia</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood; and the deriuatiue <hi>humanus</hi> is attributed to a woman in <hi>Horace, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano capite</hi> (to a womans head) <hi>cerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem pictor equinam Iungere ſi vellet, &amp;c.</hi> as appeares by what followes, <hi>mulier formoſa ſupernè;</hi> but hence cannot be any infallible concluſion drawne, that <hi>Homo</hi> is of the feminine gender; and ſo, neither by conſequence that <hi>nemo</hi> is of that gender: in this let euery one follow what hee himſelfe ſeeth beſt grounds for.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it true that</hi> Caſſida, ae, <hi>is formed of</hi> Caſſida, <hi>the accuſatiue caſe of a Greek
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2017:33"/> word</hi> Caſſis caſſidos; <hi>as</hi> Panthera <hi>of</hi> Panther, <hi>as</hi> Robinſon <hi>would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: he, and his brother <hi>Lilly</hi> herein draw in the ſame line of error: <hi>caſſis</hi> is primitiuely a latine word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that true which</hi> Robinſon <hi>hath in his rules of redundant nounes, that</hi> ador <hi>and</hi> ados <hi>are both read in the nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for <hi>ador</hi> is onely to be found, not <hi>ados;</hi> the rule may be corrected by putting <hi>odor</hi> for <hi>ador, odos</hi> for <hi>ados,</hi> for both theſe words are read in good authors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are</hi> puber <hi>and</hi> pubes <hi>of the ſame ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification, as</hi> Robinſon <hi>tels vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: <hi>pubes</hi> is properly a ſigne of ripeneſſe of age in men, at foureteene yeeres, in women at twelue, but <hi>puber</hi> ſignifies one that hath arriued at thoſe yeeres.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May thoſe luxuriant adiectiues which are deriued of</hi> Arma, iugum, neruus, &amp;c. <hi>be vſed promiſcuouſly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for though they be found in old writers, yet many of them are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2017:34"/> by thoſe which haue refined the Latine tongue: we muſt not vſe <hi>iner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> ſo frequently as <hi>inermis,</hi> nor <hi>ſubli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> but <hi>ſublimis,</hi> nor <hi>procliuus</hi> but <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliuis,</hi> not <hi>ſynceris</hi> but <hi>ſyncerus</hi> onely, not <hi>imbellus</hi> but <hi>imbellis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Adiectiues and their Compariſons.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many terminations be there of adiectiues in the poſitiue degree?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nine: all adiectiues end as one of theſe adiectiues:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SoleRS, excelleNS, locuplES, ſublimIS, &amp; audAX.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>BelligER, atque ſatVR, prefulgidVS, atque Rauenn AS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>and here wee may note by the way, that <hi>Rauennas, Arpinas</hi> are declined as <hi>Noſtras.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> vnus <hi>neuer vſed in the plurall number, except it be ioyned with a word which wanteth the ſingular num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, among the Poets, who for verſe ſake often vſe the plurall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:2017:34"/> for the ſingular, as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg. ſatis vna ſuperque vidimus excidia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What adiectiues be there which may be encreaſed, or diminiſhed in ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and yet are not compared in pure writers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgaris, vetulus, balbus, ſylueſter, equester,</hi>
               </p>
               <l>Delirus, criſpus, claudus, canuſque ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norus,</l>
               <l>Gallicus atque cicur, memor, almus, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus, egenus, &amp;c.</l>
               <p>
                  <hi>What adiectiues are not compared at all by a proper compariſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Thoſe that end in <hi>us, purum,</hi> as <hi>egregius.</hi> 2. Participials in <hi>dus,</hi> as <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendus,</hi> which is vſed by ſome in the ſuperlatiue, <hi>colendiſſimus:</hi> it were more pure to ſay, <hi>maxime,</hi> or <hi>admodum colendus.</hi> 3. Adiectiues in <hi>plex,</hi> as <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>druplex,</hi> except <hi>ſimplex, multiplex.</hi> 4. In <hi>imus,</hi> as <hi>maritimus.</hi> 5. In <hi>ivus,</hi> as <hi>fugitiuus:</hi> but yet we read <hi>festiuior, feſtiuiſſimus.</hi> 6. Deriuatiues in <hi>inus,</hi> as <hi>matutinus.</hi> 7. Compounds of <hi>fero</hi> and <hi>gero,</hi> as <hi>legifer, corniger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that true that the comparatiue doth
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:2017:35"/> ſignifie the poſitiue with</hi> magis.</p>
               <p>No: for the comparatiue doth <hi>magis ſignificare. i.</hi> hath a larger ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification then the poſitiue, though it doth not <hi>ſignificare poſitiuum cum magis,</hi> becauſe the denominatiue doth not ſignifie the <hi>Noune</hi> from which it is deriued, but the <hi>Thing</hi> after another manner: ſo the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue ſignifies a thing, not a noune.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which adiectiues want the poſitiue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, <hi>deterior, potior, ac oeyor,</hi> thoſe which are deriued of theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, comprehended in this verſe:
<q>Ante, infra, ſupra, extra, intra, vltra, poſt, prope, citra.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which adiectiues want the comparatiue degree, yet haue the ſuperlatiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe: <hi>Inclytus, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſacer, falſus, fidus, merituſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nuper, &amp; inuiius, nouus, &amp; iuriſconſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which adiectiues want the ſuperlatiue, yet haue the comparatiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe: <hi>Longinguus, iuuenis, decliuis, &amp; infinitus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:2017:35"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Atque ſenex, ingens, adoleſcens, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que propinquus. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What adiectiues ending in <hi>dus</hi> may be compared?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such as are primitiuely adiectiues, as, <hi>Iucundus, ior, iſſimus: limpidus, ior, iſſimus: faecundus, ior, iſſimus:</hi> but nounes adiectiues participials may not be compared: it is true that ſome modern writers haue compared them according to Analogie; but yet there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they haue ſwarued from the vſe of the moſt pure authors; &amp; this liberty they tooke to expreſſe the abundance of their ardent affection, reſpect and obſeruance to their Patrons and Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours; and therefore wee ſeldome or neuer finde them compared, except in the frontiſpices of Dedicatory Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. But <hi>Certiſſima loquendi magistra conſuetudo,</hi> ſaith <hi>Quintilian:</hi> we may not ſay, <hi>reuerendiſſimo viro,</hi> but <hi>reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo:</hi> not, <hi>Vir recolendiſſimae memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae,</hi> but <hi>colendae, recolendae:</hi> nor <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randiſſimus,</hi> but <hi>cum primis, vel max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imè venerandus. Goclen. Prob. l.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 22.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:2017:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>How are verbals in</hi> bilis <hi>to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not beyond the comparatiue. Wee read, <hi>formidabilis, formidabilior,</hi> but neuer, <hi>formidabiliſſimus,</hi> ſo <hi>amabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, amabilior,</hi> but neuer <hi>amabiliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How can noune ſubſtantiues be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſince they cannot receiue any increaſe of ſignification?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When a noune ſubſtantiue is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, the ſubſtance is not reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the qualitie: as <hi>paenior</hi> is as much as <hi>paeno vafrior,</hi> more crafty or vnfaithfull then a <hi>Carthaginian. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronior,</hi> as much as <hi>Nerone Saeuior,</hi> more bloudy and cruell then <hi>Nero:</hi> ſo <hi>oculiſſimus. i. dilectiſſimus;</hi> as deare to one as his eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of a Pronoune.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whence hath a Pronoune its name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quòd pro nomine ponatur.</hi> From be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſometimes put in the roome and place of a noune, ſo <hi>Scaliger</hi> defines it,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2017:36"/> 
                  <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>de C. L. L. c.</hi> 27. Amongſt the Lawyers <hi>ea,</hi> is put for <hi>mulier,</hi> and <hi>ipſa</hi> for <hi>filiafamilias:</hi> the Scholars of <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> being asked a reaſon of their Aſſertions, anſwered, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Hee hath ſaid it,</hi> that is, <hi>Pythagoras. Plaut. in Caſina. ſc. ſi ſapitis. Ipſam pro hera dixit, Ego eo, quo me Ipſa miſit:</hi> ſo wee in Engliſh ſay; the <hi>ſtoutest Hee.</hi> For the moſt couragious, or one that beares his head higheſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can one, and the ſame pronoune bee called a primitiue, a demonſtratiue, and a relatiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: but not in one and the ſame reſpect, as for example: the pronoune <hi>Ille</hi> in reſpect of its originall is a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue, becauſe it is not deriued of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, in reſpect of its demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or pointing out of ſome Perſon, or Thing a demonſtratiue, in reſpect of its relation, a relatiue, becauſe it repeates, or rehearſes ſome thing, or perſon, of which there was mention before made.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How comes it to paſſe that</hi> noſtri, <hi>and</hi> veſtri, <hi>are vſed in the genitiue caſe plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2017:37"/> as well as</hi> noſtrum, <hi>and</hi> veſtrum.</p>
               <p>Becauſe <hi>nostri,</hi> and <hi>vestri,</hi> in the genitiue ſingular, ſignifie a multitude, therefore they are vſed promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>noſtrum,</hi> and <hi>veſtrum,</hi> in the plurall genitiue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee finde in the Engliſh Rudiments.</hi> Quo, qua, quo, vel qui. <hi>Is</hi> Qui <hi>read in the ablatiue caſe in the neuter gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thinke there can ſcarce any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample bee found of that kinde: but, <hi>Qui</hi> is read in the ablatiue caſe of the maſculine, and feminine gender. <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum omnia communicem. Nemo erat, quicum eſſem lubentius, Cicer.</hi> And <hi>Virg.</hi> 2. <hi>Aeneid. Quicum partiri curas, id eſt, cum qua,</hi> ſpeaking of a woman <hi>Acca,</hi> one of the aſſociates of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milla:</hi> this is, as I ſuppoſe, an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaiſme, rather to bee obſerued then imitated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that true which</hi> Lilly <hi>hath;</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialis, Pronomini Ipſe vocatiuum tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buere videtur, cum ait, vt Martis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocetur, &amp;c. A te Iuno petat ceſton, &amp; ipſa Venus.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:2017:37"/>
               <p>No: Hee was moſt groſſely ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeene in the conſtruing of theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: if <hi>ipſa</hi> bee vnderſtood in the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiue caſe, <hi>Martial</hi> will be made to write plaine non-ſenſe: that the truth may appeare, and none may by cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitie ſucke in this error, I will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne the whole Epigram with the tranſlation thereof, it is to be found, <hi>Epig. l.</hi> 6. <hi>ep.</hi> 13.</p>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Vide doctiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi Farnabij No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas in iſtud Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramma.</note>
                        <hi>Quis te Phidiaco formatam Iulia coelo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vt quis Palladiae non putet artis opus.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Candida non tacita reſpondet imagine Lygdos;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Et placido fulget vinus in ore decor.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ludit Acidalio ſed non manus aſpera nodo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quem rapuit collo parue Cupido tuo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vt Martis reuocetur amor, ſaeui<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantis.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A te Iuno petat</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>i.</hi> à pungen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do. Ceſtus enim eſt baltheus ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> variegatus, &amp; acupictus.</note> 
                        <hi>ceſton &amp; ipſa Venus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iulia,</hi> who e're thy ſtatue ſawe, but thought</l>
                     <l>It was a maiſter-peece, by <hi>Phidias</hi> wrought?</l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:2017:38"/>
                     <l>Or artfull <hi>Pollaes?</hi> In thy beauteous face</l>
                     <l>Such liuely cunning ſhines, ſuch loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly grace,</l>
                     <l>That the white marble ſome-what ſeemes to ſay.</l>
                     <l>Thy ſmooth-ſleek hand ſeemes ſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to play</l>
                     <l>With the pure <hi>Acedulian</hi> true-loues knot:</l>
                     <l>Which, pretie <hi>Cupid,</hi> from thy necke ſhee hath got.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venus,</hi> to regayne <hi>Mars;</hi> and <hi>Iuno, Ioue,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>May aske of thee the embroidered Belt of loue.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why is</hi> Cujas <hi>handled among the pronounes? is it becauſe</hi> Cujus <hi>is there of which it ſeemes to be deriued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: <hi>Cuias</hi> is no deriuatiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune, but a primitiue noune gentile, and is referred to the fourth declen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of pronounes, becauſe of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitie of termination, and declinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the pronounes, <hi>noſtras, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtras.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:2017:38"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is that true which is in</hi> Lilly, <hi>that</hi> Ego, <hi>and</hi> Nos <hi>onely are of the firſt Perſon:</hi> Tu, <hi>and</hi> Vos <hi>of the ſecond, whenas</hi> Ipſe <hi>is alſo both of the firſt and ſecond Perſon?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ipſe</hi> is not of the firſt perſon onely, or of the ſecond perſon onely, as <hi>Ego</hi> and <hi>Tu</hi> are, but indifferently as well of the third perſon as of the firſt, or ſecond; the meaning of <hi>Lilly</hi> is, that none of the pronounes, except <hi>Ego,</hi> and <hi>Tu,</hi> are onely of the firſt, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the ſecond perſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why may not</hi> Egomet, Tute, Iſthic, Illic, <hi>bee numbred among the demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratiues, as well as</hi> Idem <hi>among the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiues?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſee no reaſon to the contrarie, if it had pleaſed the Compoſer of the <hi>Accidence,</hi> ſo to haue ranked them; if compoſition excludes them, it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes <hi>Idem</hi> alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of a Verbe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>No ſentence or propoſition can bee a part of ſpeech: how can a verbe then bee
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2017:39"/> a part of ſpeech ſince it is a ſentence. All verbes of the firſt or ſecond perſon, are ſentences, as alſo all verbes of the third perſon, as often as a certaine perſon is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood; as</hi> pluit, ningit, grandinat, Deus ſcilicet, vel natura, vel aliquid ſimile?</p>
               <p>Such propoſitions as theſe, the Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians call <hi>implicite,</hi> which are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into explicite propoſitions, by ſupplying the nominatiue caſe, and reſoluing the verbe into a participle of the preſent tenſe with the verbe <hi>ſum,</hi> thus, <hi>ſcribo,</hi> .i. <hi>ego ſum ſcribens; pugnas, tu es pugnans; pluit, coelum eſt pluens, &amp;c.</hi> an explicite propoſition cannot bee a part of ſpeech, but an implicite may, foraſmuch as it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee compleate without a ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is a verbe deponent?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Such a verbe, as amongſt ancient Authors was a verbe Commune, and had both actiue and paſſiue ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but now amongſt purer writers, <hi>depoſuit</hi> hath laid off that nature, and ſignifies onely actiuely, hauing a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2017:39"/> termination, as <hi>meditor, obliuiſcor, aggredior, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that true in the</hi> Accidence: <hi>ſuch verbes as haue no perſons are called im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſonals?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: Imperſonals are not ſo called becauſe they haue no perſons (for they haue as wee ſee) very many of them, the voyce of the third perſon both actiue and paſſiue, but becauſe they haue not any certaine ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion either of number, or perſon, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſome noune, or pronoune be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to them in an oblique caſe, as <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet me,</hi> ſeemes to be of the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and ſingular number. <hi>Oportet nos,</hi> of the firſt perſon plurall. <hi>Oportet te,</hi> of the ſecond perſon ſingular. <hi>Opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet vos,</hi> of the ſecond perſon plurall. So <hi>Lilly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are verbes Commune now in vſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Very few: we ſhall ſcarce finde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny verbes in pure Writers, that ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie both actiuely, and paſſiuely: there were ſuch amongſt the Ancients, which in ſignification did anſwere the meane voyce of the Greekes,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2017:40"/> as <hi>Linacer</hi> is of opinion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth the Indicatiue Moode ſhew a reaſon true or falſe, as the</hi> Accidence <hi>defines it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for when I ſay, <hi>Amo,</hi> I loue: I make a ſimple affirmation by this word, not any confirmation of ought by reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not there a plaine contradiction in</hi> Lilly <hi>touching the potentiall Moode?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: in his Etymologie, touching the moods of a verbe, hee hath theſe words: <hi>Potentialis ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vllum aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium adiunctum habet, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> coniunctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</hi> In the Syntaxis, of an aduerbe theſe: <hi>Dum pro dummodo alias poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiali, alias ſubiunctiuo nectitur.</hi> In the Syntaxis of a coniunction, theſe: <hi>Vt cauſalis, ſeu perfectiua coniunctio &amp;c. nunc potentiali nunc ſubiunctiuo iungi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> an euident contradiction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that true which is in the</hi> Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: <hi>the ſubiunctiue mood hath euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ſome coniunction ioyned with him, as,</hi> Cum amarem, <hi>When I loued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: in this ſpeech there are two errors. Firſt, the ſubiunctiue hath
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2017:40"/> ſometimes an aduerbe ioyned with him, as <hi>Lilly</hi> affirmes in his Syntaxis of Aduerbes. <hi>Vbi poſtquam &amp;c. inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum indicatiuis, interdum ſubiunctiuis verbis apponuntur.</hi> Againe, <hi>Simulac &amp;c. ind. &amp; ſub. adhaerent.</hi> Secondly, there is an errour in the example. For when <hi>Cum,</hi> ſignifieth <hi>When,</hi> it is not a coniunction, but an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe of Time, ſo ſaith <hi>Lilly. Vbi, postquam, &amp; cùm, temporis aduerbia &amp;c. Cùm canerem reges &amp;c.</hi> Virg.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To what purpoſe are the potentiall, and ſubiunctiue Moodes, ſince without theſe there is a perfect formation of verbs made?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you reſpect the naked manner of forming, and difference of termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, they doe not at all differ: but if you reſpect the ſignification (of which to the right interpretation of Authors, there is great conſideration to be had) the vſe of theſe Moodes is very neceſſarie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the Infinitiue Moode haue neither number nor perſon, nor nominatiue caſe before it, to what purpoſe, is that firſt
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2017:41"/> exception from</hi> verbum perſonale, &amp;c. <hi>placed in the firſt Concord,</hi> viz. Verba infiniti modi pro nominatiuo accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuum ante ſe ſtatuunt?</p>
               <p>I thinke that that exception is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſuperfluous; for how can a verbe which hath no perſon, nor number, make an exception from a verbe which hath both number, and perſon: it is in effect, as if <hi>Lilly</hi> had ſaid; from this rule can none bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, but ſuch as are not capable of exception.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whence hath the word Tenſe its ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the French word <hi>temps,</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Time,</hi> which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced <hi>Tans,</hi> and ſo <hi>Tenſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The common and receiued diuiſion of Time is in</hi> praeſens, praeteritum, futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum; <hi>how comes it to paſſe then that Grammar makes fiue Tenſes or Times?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Philoſophers ſpeake other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then the Grammarians: the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers ſearching more narrowly into the truth, and nature of things, diuide all Time into that which is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2017:41"/> paſt, preſent, and to come, becauſe if wee would ſpeake preciſely, all Time either is now, or hath beene, or ſhall bee hereafter: but the Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians who doe not ſo ſtrictly, and exactly weigh the natures of things, haue made for more facilitie in teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, fiue Tenſes of latine verbes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the proprietie of the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage. The Greekes haue eight Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, not according to the truth of the matter, but according to the vſe, and proprietie of their tongue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe you thinke of this paſſage in Lilly?</hi> Futurum, quo res in futuro gerenda ſignificatur. Hic promiſſivus modus à nonnullis vocatur.</p>
               <p>It is very faultie. Firſt, here is confuſion of termes: for, <hi>modus</hi> is here put for <hi>tempus.</hi> Secondly, the particle <hi>Hic</hi> hath reference to <hi>futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and ſo there is a ſolaeciſme, or at leaſt a ſolaecophanes; it may bee thus corrected: <hi>Hoc tempus à nonnullis vocatur promiſſivum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If</hi> Deleo, <hi>and</hi> Impleo, <hi>be compound verbes, whoſe ſimples are out of vſe;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:2017:42"/> how is it that wee finde in</hi> As in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenti, <hi>this:</hi> Leo, les, leui, inde<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Deleo deleui, pleo, ples, pleui?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lilly</hi> did not well in concealing or omitting the abrogation, and exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of theſe wordes out of the latine tongue; we may not vſe theſe out of compoſition any more then <hi>ſpecio, lacio,</hi> or <hi>cumbo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> Edormiſco <hi>ſignifie incohation, or beginning of action.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it is put for a verbe incohatiue by <hi>Lilly,</hi> but it doth not ſignifie to begin to ſleepe, but to ſleepe ſo long vntill the vapours ariſing from wine are diſperſed: ſo in <hi>Terence,</hi> in <hi>Adelp. Edormiſcam hoc villi:</hi> like to this verb are many others, which though they end in <hi>ſco,</hi> yet doe not ſignifie begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of action, or paſſion; which is euident, becauſe the Orators, Poets, and Hiſtorians, ſet before ſome of them the verbs: <hi>Caepi, incipio, incepto;</hi> before others the aduerbs. <hi>Paulatim, quotidie, magis:</hi> as for example.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Caepit erudeſcere morbus. <bibl>Virg. i.</bibl>
                  </q> 
                  <q>Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dior fieri. <bibl>Seruius.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:2017:42"/>
               <p>
                  <q>Aegreſcit<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> medendo <hi>.i.</hi> inter medendum fit aegrius.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Incipiunt agitata tumeſcere. <bibl>Virg.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Supercilia nonnunquam caneſcere inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt. <bibl>Columel.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Cum incipit, oliua nigreſcere. <bibl>idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Vbi conualeſcere caeperunt. <bibl>idem.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Cum matureſcere frumenta inciperent. <bibl>Caeſar.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Apud exteras gentes eniteſcere incepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat. <bibl>Gell.</bibl>
                  </q> with them ſame verbs are, hiſcere, làcteſcere, grandeſcere, clareſcere, iuueneſcere, <hi>found.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Tua iuſtitia floreſcat quotidie magis. <bibl>Cic.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Quotidie mihi augeſcit (<hi>.i.</hi> augetur) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis de filio aegritudo. <bibl>Ter.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Paulatim rubeſcens roſa deliteſcit, <bibl>Plin.</bibl>
                  </q> vide <hi>Goclen. Prob. l. 1. pag. 38. 39.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is <hi>Dormito</hi> a frequentatiue verbe?</p>
               <p>It is by termination, and deriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but not by ſignification: <hi>dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> ſignifies in latine what <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth in greeke, To take a nap, or to ſleepe dogs ſleepe; <hi>Dormito deſiderium po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius ſomni, aut leuiculum ſomnum, quam frequentem indicat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter Ramus, l.</hi> 16. <hi>Schol. Gram.</hi> and in that of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2017:43"/> Quando<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> bonus dormitat Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus: Quando<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</hi> is a ſigne both of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution and frequency, and ſo takes away the ſignification of frequency from <hi>dormito.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whence hath Coningation its name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A coniugando:</hi> becauſe in euery Conjugation after one, and the ſame manner of varying of finall termina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions many verbes are ioyned, as it were vnder the ſame <hi>iugum,</hi> or yoake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haue all verbs of the first Coniuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> a <hi>long before</hi> re <hi>and</hi> ris?</p>
               <p>No: for <hi>Do,</hi> and ſome of its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds:<note place="margin">To theſe may be alſo added, <hi>venundare,</hi> of <hi>venum &amp; dare,</hi> as I ſuppoſe.</note> as, <hi>Peſſundo, circundo,</hi> make <hi>dăre. Circundăre, Peſſundăre. Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> and the Poſer of the <hi>Accidence,</hi> adde <hi>ſecundo, ſecundăre:</hi> but this is not a compound of <hi>Do. Secundo,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies to make proſperous, deriued of <hi>ſecundus,</hi> proſperous, fauourable, and hath <hi>a</hi> long.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If all verbs be of the firſt Coniugation, which haue</hi> a <hi>long before</hi> re <hi>and</hi> ris, <hi>then it ſeemes,</hi> doceare, docearis; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diare, audiaris, <hi>be of the first Coniuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:2017:43"/>
               <p>The meaning of that is, not that all verbes that in any moode haue <hi>a</hi> long before <hi>re</hi> and <hi>ris,</hi> be of the firſt Coniugation, but ſuch as haue <hi>a</hi> long before <hi>re</hi> in the infinitiue moode of the actiue forme, as <hi>amare,</hi> and before <hi>ris</hi> in the ſecond perſon of the preſent Tenſe of the indicatiue moode of the paſſiue forme: as <hi>gratularis,</hi> are of the firſt Coniugation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why doe you ſay of the actiue, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue forme, and not of the actiue and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue voyce?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe there be many verbes neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which are not actiue, and yet in coniugation follow the forme of the actiue verbes, and many verbes depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, which though they be not paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue in ſignification, yet in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iugation follow the forme of the paſſiue verbs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Vpon</hi> As in Praeſenti.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The verbe</hi> Lauo, <hi>which</hi> Lilly <hi>ſaith, is of the first Coniugation, makes</hi> lauĕre <hi>in the Infinit. the last ſyllable ſaue one ſhort; and</hi> ſtrideo, caveo, ferveo, <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king</hi> fervere, ſtridere, cavere, <hi>are found
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2017:44"/> with</hi> e <hi>ſhort before</hi> re <hi>in the infinitiue of the ſecond Coniugation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis true: but <hi>lauĕre</hi> is not of <hi>lauo, lavas,</hi> but of <hi>lauo lauis,</hi> which was of the third conjug. amongſt the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and ſo vſed by <hi>Virgil</hi> in his <hi>Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicks</hi> and <hi>Aeneids,</hi> and <hi>feruere,</hi> and <hi>ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere</hi> are found with <hi>e</hi> ſhort, but thus conjugated, they are now growne out of vſe; we are not to imitate the old Authors in theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> ſpondeo <hi>geminate the firſt ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable in the</hi> praeteritum, <hi>and make</hi> ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondi?</p>
               <p>No: herein <hi>Lilly</hi> was deceiued, and deceiued the Poſer of the <hi>Accidence,</hi> and the Conſtruer of <hi>Lillies</hi> rules, who tranſcribe it ſo: in the refined copies of the moſt incorrupt Authors, <hi>ſpondeo</hi> is found to make the <hi>praeteritum ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondi,</hi> not <hi>ſpoſpondi.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Panſa aut morte aut victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria ſe ſatisfactu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondit <hi>Cic.</hi> Dependendum tibi eſt, quod mihi pro illo ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondiſti. <hi>Idem.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> crepo <hi>found of the third coniuga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as</hi> Lilly <hi>affirmeth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: the pure Writers, who are to bee our Preſidents, vſe it in the firſt conjugation: <hi>Intestina tibi crepant.</hi> Plaut. <hi>Quis poſt vina grauem militiam, &amp; pauperiem crepat.</hi> Hor.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:2017:44"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> quiniſco <hi>found in any good au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: the true verbe is <hi>conquiniſco,</hi> which is a ſimple verbe, and ſo ſet downe by <hi>Nebriſſenſis,</hi> and <hi>Ramus,</hi> not a compound of <hi>con,</hi> and <hi>quiniſco,</hi> as <hi>Lilly</hi> imagined, any more then <hi>condio,</hi> or <hi>conſulo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> nexo, nexis, nexui, <hi>read in the third coniugation, as</hi> Lilly <hi>tels vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it is onely read in the firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iugation, <hi>nexo, nex as, nexare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> cambio campſi <hi>found in any pure author?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it is a barbarous word, not to be vſed by any that would write pure latine; it is onely found in the old Grammarian <hi>Priſcian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> Praecurro <hi>make</hi> Precucurri <hi>in the</hi> preterium?</p>
               <p>No: it can ſcarce be ſo found in any good author.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> tracto alwaies <hi>in compoſition change the first vowell into</hi> e?</p>
               <p>No: for we read <hi>retracto: vulnera cruda retractat. Ouid. Pedamenta re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractare. Columel.</hi> So likewiſe <hi>Pertra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto.
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2017:45"/> Pertractare Philoſophiam. Cic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> habeo <hi>alwayes in compoſition change the first vowell into</hi> i, <hi>as</hi> Lilly <hi>ſaith?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for we read <hi>poſthabeo:</hi> as, <hi>poſtha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo famae pecuniam,</hi> in the Syntaxis.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> exculpo <hi>a compound of</hi> ex <hi>and ſcalpo?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeemes rather to be compounded of <hi>ex</hi> and <hi>ſculpo:</hi> for the ſimple word <hi>ſculpo</hi> is in vſe, as <hi>Ouid. Arte Mira ſculpſit ebur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is vulſum</hi> regularly formed of <hi>velli:</hi> according to that, <hi>Dat velli vulſum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It ſeemes rather to be formed of the other <hi>preteritum</hi> of <hi>vello</hi> viz. <hi>vulſi.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is that rule of</hi> Lilly <hi>to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood,</hi> Verba in or admittunt ex poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riore ſupino praeteritum.</p>
               <p>It is to be vnderſtood of ſuch verbs whoſe actiues haue the latter ſupine, of the which the preterperfectenſe paſſiue may be formed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What then ſhall wee ſay concerning verbes deponent, and commune, which end in</hi> or, <hi>and haue a preterperfect tenſe, which they cannot forme of a latter
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2017:45"/> ſupine: ſince they haue no verbs actiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lilly</hi> doth ſay nothing of this point. I am of opinion that verbs actiue are to be fained, of whoſe latter ſupine theſe verbs would regularly forme their preterperfect tenſe, if ſuch actiues were in vſe: as for example, ſuppoſe that there were ſuch a verbe as <hi>laeto, laetas, laetaui,</hi> of the latter ſupine of this verbe <hi>laetatu,</hi> regularly ſhall be formed, <hi>laetatus ſum, vel fui.</hi> So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the ſupine <hi>criminatu,</hi> of the fained verbe <hi>crimino, nas:</hi> wee may forme the <hi>preteritum, criminatus, ſum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is she meaning of that verſe in Grammer?</hi> Maereo ſum maeſtus ſed Phocae nomen habetur.</p>
               <p>That the neutropaſſiue verbe <hi>moe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reo</hi> hath <hi>maestus ſum</hi> for its <hi>preteritum;</hi> but the Grammarian <hi>Phocas</hi> did think <hi>maestus</hi> rather to be a noune: this verſe might very well be ſpared.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Gerunds.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whence hath a Gerund its name?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:2017:46"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quòd rei gerendae, &amp; administrandae exprimat ſignificationem.</hi> Becauſe it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth the ſignification of a thing to be done, or executed. Some would haue the name to be giuen <hi>a gerenda duplici ſignificatione, nempe actiua &amp; paſſiua ſub vna voce:</hi> but ſince there are ſo few Gerunds that ſignifie paſſiuely, and thoſe which doe, almoſt all growne out of vſe, I thinke that is not the reaſon of the name: in this, and many other tearmes of art we are left to diuine of the reaſons of the impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the names.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that generally true which wee finde in the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Rudiments. Gerunds haue both the actiue and paſſiue ſignification: as,</hi> amandi <hi>of louing, or being loued:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mando, <hi>in louing, or in being loued:</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandum, <hi>to loue, or to be loued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: the greateſt part of Gerunds are vſed actiuely, very few paſſiuely; and in that kinde of vſe, there ſeemes to be an Archaiſme.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:2017:46"/>
               <head>Of the Supines.</head>
               <p>Doth the latter ſupine ſignifie paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely onely, for the moſt part as is in the <hi>Accidence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No: it is alwaies of a paſſiue ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of a Participle.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Since there are in truth but three</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora <hi>of Participles,</hi> praeſens, praeteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, futurum, <hi>is it proper to ſay,</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora participiorum ſunt quatuor, <hi>by ſubdiuiding the future into the participle in</hi> rus, <hi>of the actiue, and neutrall ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and the participle in</hi> dus, <hi>of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ſignification?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thinke no: <hi>Lilly</hi> might as well haue ſaid, as I ſuppoſe, there be fiue <hi>tempora,</hi> foraſmuch as the participles of the future tenſe of a verbe actiue, and a verbe neuter ending in <hi>rus,</hi> doe differ in time as much among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as a participle of the future tenſe of a verbe paſſiue doth from ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:2017:47"/> of them: if the actiue and paſſiue ſignification do diſtinguiſh their <hi>times,</hi> hee might then haue ſaid in his diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Tenſes, Tempora ſunt ſex, praeſent, imperfectum &amp; futurum duplex, actiuae, &amp; paſſiuae vocis:</hi> nay, hee might haue ſaid, <hi>Tempora ſunt decem quinque acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uae, quinque paſſiuae vocis:</hi> but of this let the iudicious paſſe ſentence. I ſpeake with ſubmiſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If in that example of the</hi> Accidence, Legend is veteribus proficis, <hi>a partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the future in</hi> dus, <hi>haue the ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of a participle of the preſent tenſe: how is it that</hi> Lilly <hi>in his Syntaxis, ſaith that in a like example a Gerund is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a noune adiectiue: as,</hi> Cur adeo delectaris criminibus inferendis?</p>
               <p>Truth is but one, on which ſide truth weighs heauier, I leaue to Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians to determine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth a perfect verbe neuter forme onely two participles regularly, one of the preſent tenſe, and another of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in</hi> rus?</p>
               <p>Yes: for though we read <hi>vigilandus, carendus,</hi> participles in <hi>dus,</hi> and <hi>trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatus,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2017:47"/> regnatus:</hi> but ſome of theſe and the like may be ended in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner irregular, vſed onely by the Poets, whom it is not ſafe in all things to imitate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But it ſeemes that regularly there come of ſome neutrals three participles; as of</hi> gaudeo, gaudens, gauiſus, gauiſurus: <hi>of</hi> audeo, audens, auſus, auſurus: fido, fidens, fiſus, fiſurus, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of which onely two partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples come, muſt be onely neutrals; ſuch are not theſe: for theſe are <hi>neutro paſſiues,</hi> which ſince they differ from them in the manner of coniugation, no maruell if they differ from them in forming their participles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why are they called Neutro-paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiues?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe though they be neuters, yet they forme a <hi>Praeteritum,</hi> after che manner of verbs paſſiue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How doe neutro-paſſiues, and paſſiue-neutrals differ?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neutro-paſſiues, although they haue the preterperfect tenſe of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiues, yet they retaine the ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2017:48"/> of neuters; as, <hi>ſoleo, ſolitus ſum,</hi> but paſſiue neutrals, though they end in <hi>o,</hi> yet they haue a paſſiue ſignification, and gouern the ſame caſe that paſſiues doe, as <hi>vagulo, exulo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But it ſeemes there be ſome participles of the paſſiue voyce, which come of verbs neuter; for wee read,</hi> excurſus, aratus, laboratus excurrendus arandus, labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randus.</p>
               <p>Theſe are formed of imperſonall neuters, which are onely found in the third perſon of the paſſiue voice, but when Grammer ſaith, that onely two participles are formed of neuters, it meanes perſonall neuters of the actiue forme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not verbs and participles of the actiue ſignification ſometimes vſed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely,</hi> &amp; contrà?</p>
               <p>Yes; as for example, <hi>Voluens pro volutus,</hi> as <hi>Turneb.</hi> 30. <hi>Aduerſar.</hi> 19. ſaith: <hi>Certè hinc Romanos olim voluen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus annis. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</hi> 1. <hi>Aen. Sparſus pro ſpargens. Priùs hauſtus ſparſus aqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ore fore. Virg.</hi> 4. <hi>Geor.</hi> So <hi>Cèrda<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Velata pro velans. Senec. in Herc. At.
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2017:48"/> Aet. ſc. Flete. Adeſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſequi iuſſa ſagit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas Totum pennis velata diem.</hi> Plaut. in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. Glorioſ. ſc. ſatin'. <hi>Irae leniunt.</hi> i. <hi>leniuntur.</hi> Virg. 2. Aeneid. <hi>Inſinuat pro inſinuatur,</hi> as <hi>Seruius</hi> conceiues. <hi>Tum vero tremefacta nouis per pectora cunctis Inſinuat pauor.</hi> idem. <hi>vertere pro verſa ſunt. Et totae in ſolidam glaciem vertere lacunae.</hi> vide <hi>Robig. Dict. Critic. l.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Aduerbs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not</hi> minus <hi>and</hi> male <hi>aduerbs of denying?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, though they bee omitted by Lilly: <hi>Minus pro non in Varro. Non mirum ſi caecutis minus, aurum enim non perſtringit oculos. Si minus intelligitur,</hi> if men vnderſtand not. <hi>Cic.</hi> So <hi>male.</hi> Petron. <hi>Quas ſtruxit opes male ſuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net. Malè ſanus,</hi> not well in his wit. <hi>Male ſobrius,</hi> not ſober.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe not two negatiue aduerbs denie more ſtrongly ſometimes in latine, as well as in greeke?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: So, <hi>Virg.</hi> 2. <hi>Georg.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:2017:49"/>
                  <l>Non ego cuncta meis amplecti verſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus opto,</l>
                  <l>Non mihi ſi linguae centum ſint, oraque centum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et Aeneid.</hi> 6. <hi>Ne pueri, ne tanta animis aſſueſcite bella. Tull.</hi> 7. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1. <hi>Haec tibi ridicula videntur, non</hi> n. <hi>ades quae ſi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deres, lacrymas non teneres, non.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe not particles of denying ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times imply an affirmation,</hi> &amp; contrà?</p>
               <p>Yes: as for example, <hi>Virg.</hi> 2. <hi>Geor. Et pro neque. Nec ſcabie, &amp; falſa laedit rubigine ferrum. Et pro Sed. Cic. Muto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cauſas non grauate &amp; gratuito de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendere.</hi> So <hi>Senec. Oratio oſtendit illum non eſſe ſyncerum, &amp; habere aliquid ficti. Aut. pro nec. Vir.</hi> 4. <hi>Aen. Sed nullis ille mouetur fletibus, aut vocos vllus tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis audit. Neque pro &amp;, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</hi> 5. <hi>Ecl. Nulla neque amnem Libauit quadrupes nec graminis attigit herbam. Iuuenal. Sat.</hi> 5. <hi>Omnia Graecè. Cum ſit tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe magis nostris neſcire latinè:</hi> where in <hi>neſcire</hi> the verbe <hi>ſciuut</hi> is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, which belongs to <hi>omnia Graece</hi> before. <hi>Mart.</hi> 5. <hi>Ep.</hi> 53. <hi>Exprimere Aue Latinum,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>non
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2017:49"/> potes Graecum:</hi> where in <hi>non potes, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> which belongs to the former com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma is to be vnderſtood: ſo <hi>Tac. Ann.</hi> 13 <hi>Deeſſe nobis terra in quae viuimus, in qua moriamur non poteſt. Idem. Ann</hi> 12. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippina filio dare imperium, tolerare im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritantem nequibat:</hi> out of <hi>nequibat, quibat</hi> is to be ſupplied. <hi>Robig. Dict. Crit. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>Lilly <hi>makes</hi> ſit ita, ſit ſane <hi>aduerbs of granting,</hi> id eſt, hoc eſt, quaſi dicas, <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbs of explaning: are they aduerbs in truth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: euery aduerbe is a ſimple ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle word, theſe are ſentences, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Syntaxis, not Etymologie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Coniunctions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not it a contradiction</hi> in adiecto, <hi>to ſay, a coniunction diſiunctiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for a coniunction diſiunctiue conioynes the words, by diſioyning the matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> Lilly <hi>ſpeake logically, when he ſaith</hi> ſunt dictiones que nunc aduerbia, nunc coniunctiones, nunc praepoſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eſſe inueniuntur vt cum.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:2017:50"/>
               <p>No: for there is no other word of that nature, except <hi>Come.</hi> He here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſpeaks like that Grammarian, who made this rule in <hi>ol,</hi> maſc. <hi>Suut. vt Sol.</hi> whereas it ſhould haue run thus, <hi>in ol vnicum maſculinum eſt, vt Sol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> que <hi>alwayes an Encliticke?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: wee finde it ſometimes put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the word it couples, as that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph of <hi>Tibullus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Hic iacet immiti conſumptus morte Tibullus,</l>
                  <l>Meſſalam terra dùm ſequitur, que mari.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg. Ipſe ego cana legam tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra lanugine mala. Castaneas, que nuces.</hi> i. <hi>Castaneas &amp; nuces. Caſtaneae,</hi> and <hi>nuces</hi> are diſtinguiſhed, as ſaith <hi>Plinie, l.</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 28. and ſo they are here too, as <hi>Scal.</hi> thinke. <hi>de C. LL. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 177. <hi>Ouid. l.</hi> 2. <hi>de Arte,</hi> alluding to this verſe, makes a diſtinction betwixt them:
<q>
                     <l>Affert aut vras, aut quas Amacillis amabit,</l>
                     <l>Et nunc castaneas, nunc amat illa nuces.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:2017:50"/>
               <head>Of a Prepoſition.</head>
               <p>Did <hi>Lilly</hi> doe well to handle the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimen of Prepoſitions in Etymologie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No: herein he confounds Etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie and Syntaxis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of an Interiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why is an Interiection ſo called?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod interijciatur:</hi> becauſe it is <hi>caſt in</hi> as a ſodaine eiaculation, expreſſing in an abrupt faſhion, ſome paſſion of the minde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of SYNTAXIS.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHence hath Syntaxis its name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>con,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ordinatio:</hi> becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is ſet out the fit and regular coordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and ſtructure of ſimple words in clauſes and ſentences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:2017:51"/>
               <head>Of the firſt Concord.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe you thinke of the ſecond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception from</hi> verbum perſonale, <hi>viz.</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſonalia praecedentem, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I thinke it might be ſpared as well as the firſt: either this place is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper to treate of imperſonals, or elſe there is a tautologie in repeating the ſame rule afterward; nay, to ſpeak truth, this exception is abſurd: it is in effect thus much; all verbes perſonall agree with their nom. caſes in number and perſon, except verbes imperſonall, which are altogether vncapable of a nominatiue caſe before them, which is plaine <hi>non-ſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not nounes which are not colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues ſometimes conſtrued as if they were ſuch?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as for example; <hi>Plaut. in Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chid. Scen. Meamne. Et ego (Chryſalus) te, &amp; illum mactamus infortunio:</hi> the Pronoune <hi>ego</hi> here is comprehenſiue, as if <hi>Chryſalus</hi> being one, did oppoſe himſelfe againſt two, and that hee
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:2017:51"/> might match them, he ſpeaks of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as of two. <hi>Scal. de Cauſ. L. L. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 30. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irg.</hi> 9. <hi>Aeneid. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>os</hi> o <hi>Calliope precor aſpic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e canenti. Alcmena in Plaut. Amph. Sc. Satin.</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Amphitruo</hi> alone ſaith: <hi>Quis igitur niſi vos.</hi> The perſon of a King re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents many: thence that forme, <hi>Nos Iacobus Dei gratia, &amp;c. man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not ſometimes the number of the verbs varied in the ſame comma, though referred to the ſame thing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: ſo we read in <hi>Tully, ad Att. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2. <hi>Nunc fac vt ſciam quo die te vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuri ſumus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the ſecond Concord.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>May not an adiectiue put after two ſubstantiues of diuers genders, or numbers ſometimes agree with the latter, as well as with the former?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: the adiectiue may ſometimes indifferently accord with either of the ſubſtantiues; for we finde in <hi>Tully, Non omnis error ſtultitia eſt dicenda:</hi> and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:2017:52"/> in <hi>Liuy, Gens vniuerſa veneti appellati.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not an adiectiue ſometimes put alone (as it were a ſubstantiue) whoſe ſubſtantiue is to be vnderſtood and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: and that very elegantly: ſo we reade, <hi>tribuo tibi primas</hi> .i. <hi>primas partes. Amplecti ambabus</hi> .i. <hi>ambabus manibus: Aſpergere frigida</hi> .i. <hi>frigida aqua:</hi> it is an immitation of the Greekes, who ſay <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>.i.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ad rectam .i. lineam,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ab vna .i. voce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What if two adiectiues concur together in the ſame ſentence?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then one of them putteth on the nature of a ſubſtantiue: <hi>Crudelem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicum intemperans aeger faeit:</hi> here <hi>aeger</hi> is taken ſubſtantiuely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If that the adiectiue is to agree with the ſubſtantiue in caſe, gender, and number, what thinke you of theſe exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which ſeeme to ouerthrow that rule,</hi> eſt quod ſperemus Deos bonis benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturum. Aruſpices dixerunt omnia ex ſententia proceſſurum. Non putaui haec eam facturum?</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:2017:52"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Ramus</hi> in his Grammaticall Scholia's ſaith, that in theſe, and in ſuch like examples, thoſe wordes which ſeeme to be Participles, are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed verbs of the infinitiue moode and future tenſe of the actiue forme, hauing <hi>eſſe</hi> vnderſtood: <hi>in cuius ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam pedibus eo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that true latine in</hi> Plautus, <hi>where he calls</hi> Venus, <hi>Deum indignam?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Paen. in Scen. Dij illum.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: the Heathen did thinke all their gods were both Male and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, according to that of <hi>Orpheus.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>Iupiter &amp; mas eſt, &amp; neſcia foemina mortis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>So <hi>Venus,</hi> and other goddeſſes haue the title <hi>Deus</hi> giuen to them: ſo <hi>Virg. l.</hi> 2. <hi>Aeneid. Deſcendo, ac ducente Deo flammam inter, &amp; hostes Expedior.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crob. Sat. 3. c. 7. ſaith, it is ſo to bee read. <hi>Idem Aeneid.</hi> 2. <hi>Pollentem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deum Venerem. Seruius</hi> and <hi>Acte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus</hi> doe approue of that reading. <hi>Heu fortuna quis eſt crudelior in nos Te Deus.</hi> Hor. 2. Ser. 8. <hi>Lucret. l.</hi> 2.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:2017:53"/> 
                  <hi>Terram Deum matrem appellat. Sequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſuperbos vltor à tergo Deus</hi> .i. <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſis.</hi> Senec. <hi>Virg. Aeneid.</hi> 7. <hi>Alecto Deus appellatur. Nec dextrae erranti Deus abfuit.</hi> In like manner <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> for his effeminateneſſe was called <hi>Vxorius:</hi> and <hi>Liuia</hi> for her wiſedome was ſtiled, <hi>Stolatus Vlyſſes.</hi> Suet. <hi>vide Robig. Lex. Crit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not two or three adiectiues ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ioyned to one ſubſtantiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as for example. <hi>Criſpiſulcans igneum fulmen.</hi> Cic. <hi>Ob egregiam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignem fidem.</hi> Idem. <hi>Ad domeſticae exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miae eius fiduciae acta veniamus.</hi> Val. Max. <hi>Sanctiſſimus genealis torus.</hi> Idem. <hi>Pulcherrima praepes Laeua volauit auis.</hi> Ennius apud Cic. de Diuin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not ſomtimes two adiectiues cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled together, vſed for one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as for example. <hi>Sarta-tecta praecepta.</hi> Plaut. <hi>Purus-putus aſinus.</hi> Varro apud Nonium. <hi>Novum-vetus vinum bibo.</hi> Varro. <hi>Nouo-veteri mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo medeor.</hi> Idem. So, <hi>Deus optimus-maximus. Graio-Graeci.</hi> Ennius apud Feſtum. <hi>Ruta-caeſa.</hi> apud Ieſ.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:2017:53"/>
               <head>Of the third Concord.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the Relatiue agree with the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent, in Gender, Number, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; how is it that we finde in</hi> Terence. Vbi eſt ille ſcelus, qui me perdidit? Qui <hi>the Relatiue is of the maſcul. gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and</hi> ſcelus <hi>the Antecedent of the neuter?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scelus</hi> is here put for <hi>ſcelestus,</hi> as elſewhere <hi>Senium</hi> for <hi>Senex</hi> by a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonymie of the adjunct; ſo the ſenſe is made good: or <hi>qui</hi> by the figure <hi>Hyponaea</hi> hath reference to <hi>ſcelestus,</hi> to bee vnderſtood in <hi>ſcelus</hi> by the iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Readers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In that example;</hi> Eſt locus in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, quod Tullianum appellatur, <hi>and the like; as,</hi> Bene audiri, qui eſt recte factoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fructus omnes ferre volumus: <hi>and;</hi> Hodie, quae eſt altera dies Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecoſtes, venit ad me nuntius, <hi>where the Relatiue put betweene two Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, agrees with the latter, is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction proper to the Latines?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it is an imitation of the greeks,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:2017:54"/> who haue the ſame conſtruction. So <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and thus <hi>Tully. Ne ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellaueris conſilium, quae vis, ac neceſſitas appellanda est.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe you thinke of that example:</hi> Noſtros vidiſti flentis ocellos?</p>
               <p>In it there is a ſolaeciſme, or at leaſt a ſolaecophanes, the Poet ſhould haue ſaid regularly, if his verſe would haue ſuffered him, either <hi>nostros flentium,</hi> or <hi>meos flentis,</hi> to make vp the conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: we muſt vnderſtand in <hi>noſtros, meos,</hi> in <hi>meos mei.</hi> vide <hi>Goclen. Prob. Gram. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 131.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> Imperium, &amp; dignitas quae pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tijſti; <hi>a fit example of that rule in the Engliſh Syntaxis: many Antecedents ſingular hauing a coniunction copulatiue betweene them, will haue a relatiue plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, which relatiue ſhall agree with the Antecedent of the most worthy Gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for here the relatiue agrees with the antecedent of the moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy gender, <hi>viz.</hi> the Neuter. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, if this bee a true example, that exception ſubjoyned of Things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:2017:54"/> life is ſuperfluous, for it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception to it ſelfe; for to ſpeake truth, to that rule doth this example apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Imperium,</hi> and <hi>Dignitas</hi> being things without life: of that rule ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Antecedents, &amp;c. this or the like example ſhould haue beene giuen. <hi>Rex, &amp; Regina, quos tu beatos praedicas, ſunt mortales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that example;</hi> Felix quem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt aliena pericula cautum, <hi>properly rendred in Engliſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it ſhould not haue beene ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred; <hi>Happy is he &amp;c. to beware:</hi> for <hi>cautum</hi> is not here the firſt ſupine of <hi>caueo,</hi> neither can be (for it is not put after a verbe, ſignifying mouing to a place, but an adjectiue) the verſe ſhould therefore haue beene thus tranſlated: <hi>Happy is hee whom others harmes make wary.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the conſtruction of Noune Subſtantiues.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth not a Subſtantiue ſometimes gouerne two genitiue caſes, or more?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:2017:55"/>
               <p>Yes: wee reade in <hi>Cicero. Iamne ſentis bellua, quae ſit hominum querela frontis tuae?</hi> where <hi>querela</hi> gouernes <hi>hominum,</hi> and <hi>frontis. Sed quae naturae principia ſint ſocietatis humanae repeten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum altiùs videtur.</hi> idem. <hi>Procreatio Dei rerum humanarum. Aristotelis Philoſophorum Principis arcanorum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae theoremata.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not two ſubſtantiues ſometimes linked together by a line, which the Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians call</hi> Hyphen, <hi>vſed for one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: ſuch wordes are found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Lawyers; as, <hi>Placitum-conſenſum.</hi> Vlpian. <hi>Munus-donum.</hi> Modeſt. <hi>Actio-petitio.</hi> Calliſtrat. <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio-conductio.</hi> Labeo. <hi>Obiurgat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>-cenſor.</hi> Macrob.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not a noune in it ſelfe a compound, and ſo one, ſometimes diuided in reſpect of conſtruction?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as in this example. <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ille magis iuriſconſultus quam iuſtitiae fuit.</hi> The word <hi>Iuriſconſultus</hi> is one in it ſelfe, but to be diuided in the rection of <hi>iustitiae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not adiectiues of the maſculine
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:2017:55"/> or feminine gender vſed ſometimes ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiuely, as well as adiectiues of the neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: 1. <hi>Malc.</hi> as, <hi>die natalis ſui.</hi> Marc. <hi>Humanus pro Homo.</hi> Cic. ad Att. l. 3. ep. 21. <hi>Ego autem tibi affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo (poſſum falli vt humanus) à me non habere. Phaethon,</hi> the epithite of the Sunne vſed ſubſtantiuely in <hi>Aenei.</hi> 5. ſaith <hi>Cerdo. Auroram Phaethontis equi iam luce vehebant,</hi> in <hi>Aeneid.</hi> 1. <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium Dido Tyria regit vrbe profecta Germanum</hi> (.i. <hi>fratrem) fugiens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Foem.</hi> Virg. 1. Aeneid. <hi>Implen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur veteris Bacchi, pinguiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ferinae</hi> .i. <hi>carnis ferinae,</hi> Senec. 1. de Benef. 5. <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perator aliquem torquibus, muroli, &amp; ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uica donat</hi> .i. <hi>corona.</hi> &amp; Plin. l. 8. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grae lanarum nullum colorem bibunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Neutr.</hi> as, <hi>Strata viarum. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mara curarum. Singula capitum. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funda camporum. Praerupta collium. Montium ardua, opaca locorum, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not ſometimes ſubſtantiues put in the place of adiectiues?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: ſo, <hi>Nihil pro Nullo apud <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pianum.</hi> &amp; Virg. Aeneid. 1.</p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:2017:56"/>
               <p>Regales inter menſas, laticemque Lyaeum <hi>.i.</hi> Bacchicum.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe not ſome ſubſtantiues verball go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the ſame caſe that their verbs doe, of which they are deriued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as for example; wee reade <hi>exul à patria,</hi> as well as <hi>exultat à pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria; Diſceſſus ab vrbe,</hi> as well as <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcedere ab vrbe,</hi> We reade <hi>obtemperare legibus,</hi> and <hi>inſtituta est obtemperatio ſcriptis legibus:</hi> in <hi>Tully</hi> we reade in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery claſſicall Author, <hi>Capite dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nui, praefici praetorio,</hi> and <hi>Iulius Scaliger</hi> hath; <hi>Capite diminutio.</hi> Suetonius, <hi>Praefectus praetorio.</hi> Wee reade <hi>domum eo, redeo,</hi> and <hi>domum itio, reditio,</hi> in Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar. <hi>Faueo authoritati &amp;, fautor autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritati. Naſcor à muliere, &amp;, natiuitas à muliere:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Rod. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clen. obſeru. Linguae Lat. p. <hi>126.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>erudior à magistro; &amp;, ab optimo magiſtro optima inuentutis eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What ſubſtantiues gouerne an abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue caſe with the prepoſition</hi> Cum?</p>
               <p>Such as ſignifie ſocietie, conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and friendſhip, as, <hi>Amicitia, familiaritas, conſuetudo cum aliquo.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:2017:56"/> Ciceroni cum Attico magna interceſſit familiaritas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not</hi> Opus <hi>read conſtrued with an ablatiue caſe of the participle of the preter tenſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes, and that very elegantly: as for example, <hi>Priuſquam incipias con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulto, &amp; vbi conſuleris mature facto opus est,</hi> Saluſt. <hi>Opus est maturato,</hi> Liuie. <hi>Quod parato opus eſt para,</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. <hi>Opus eſt viſo, &amp; cauto,</hi> Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the conſtruction of Adiectiues.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>May an adiectiue in the neuter gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der put ſubſtantiuely, gouerne any other adiectiue alſo, put ſubſtantiuely in the genitiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: no adjectiue put as a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiue, can gouerne another adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue which is declined with three articles, but onely ſuch a one as is varied by three terminations, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may ſay: <hi>Aliquid mali, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid abſurdi, honeſti, boni,</hi> we cannot
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:2017:57"/> ſay, <hi>aliquid vtilis, aliquid impoſſibilis &amp;c.</hi> neither can we ſay, <hi>Nihil talis</hi> for <hi>Nihil tale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> Lilly <hi>ſpeake properly, when hee expreſſeth certaine nounes of num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by</hi> certa numeralia?</p>
               <p>No; he ſpeakes barbarouſly: for <hi>certus</hi> is neuer put for <hi>quidam</hi> in any good and claſſicall Writer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe you thinke of that rule,</hi> Comparatiua &amp; ſuperlatiua accepta partitiuè genitivum, vnde &amp; genus ſortiuntur, exigunt?</p>
               <p>This rule is good: It had beene well <hi>Lilly</hi> would haue furniſhed vs with ſome examples of it; in theſe which follow, his defect ſhall bee ſupplied. <hi>Ignis omnium elementorum eſt efficaciſſimum, &amp; violentiſſimum. Supremus, extremuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> omnium affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuum in foemina eſt zelotypia. Finis cauſarum omnium nobiliſſima eſt. Mors vltimum, ſummum, grauiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, &amp; acerbiſſimum omnium terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In theſe ſpeeches,</hi> Magnam partem conſulatus tui abfui. <hi>Cic.</hi> Illud tibi
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:2017:57"/> aſſentior. <hi>Idem.</hi> Menedemi vicem miſeret. <hi>Ter.</hi> Solicitus vicem Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoris. <hi>Liu.</hi> Maeſtus ſuam vicem. <hi>Curt.</hi> Caetera bonus. <hi>Cic. Why are</hi> partem, Illud vicem, caetera, <hi>the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſatiue caſe, and by what rule of Lilly?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lilly</hi> hath no rule to ſhewe the reaſon of this conſtruction: it is in truth a greeke Atticiſme: for the greekes put the accuſatiue caſe after verbes, and adiectiues after that manner: <hi>ſic,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem alicuius iraſci,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>perdidiſti nos quantum in te eſt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>omnibus ſapiens.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When is an adiectiue conſtrued with an accuſatiue caſe, with a prepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When Aptitude, propenſitie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, object, or finall cauſe is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as,
<q>
                     <l>Procliuis à labore ad libidinem.</l>
                     <l>Furtum ingenioſus ad omne.</l> 
                     <hi>Aſſuetus ad bellum. Rudis ad arma. Studio eloquentiae non aliud in ciuitate noſtra, vel ad vtilitatem fructuoſius,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:2017:58"/> vel ad dignitatem amplius, vel ad vrbis famam pulchrius, vel ad totius imperij, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> omnium gentium notitiam illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrius excogitari poteſt.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Quint.</bibl>
                  </q> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cei habiles ad pedes.</hi> 
                     <bibl>Cic.</bibl>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>Aptus natus ad ſingularem dicendi faculta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that example of</hi> adiectiua quae ad copiam, <hi>viz.</hi> at feſſae referunt multa ſe nocte minores Crura thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo plena.</p>
               <p>No: the Compoſer of the <hi>Engliſh Rudiments,</hi> and <hi>Lilly</hi> vnderſtood not (as it ſeemes) <hi>Virgils Syntaxis,</hi> and therefore corrected the originall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting it to bee faultie: and the Conſtruer of the Syntaxis ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes it, and tranſlates it. But <hi>Virgil</hi> wrote not <hi>plena,</hi> but <hi>plenae:</hi> the verſe is thus to be conſtrued: the leſſer <hi>Bees</hi> doe returne home wearie late at night (<hi>plenae crura</hi> .i. <hi>haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes crura plena thyme</hi>) Hauing their ſhankes full of thyme; in which there is a Synechdoche, or figure, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vſed by that excellent Poet, as<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ecl.</hi> 1. <hi>Sepes Byb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aeis apibus florem depaſta ſalicti</hi> .i. <hi>habens florem depaſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> So likewiſe: <hi>Os humeroſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Deo ſimilis.</hi> ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So, <hi>Faciem mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus &amp; ora</hi> .i. <hi>habens faciem mutatam;</hi> or it maybe there is an imitation of the Greekes who in ſuch ſpeeches make an <hi>ellipſis</hi> of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:2017:58"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe not adiectiues of comparing or exceeding, gouerne an ablatiue caſe of the word, which ſignifies the meaſure of exceeding, as well as verbes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: for wee may as well ſay, <hi>Cicero praeſtantior est omnibus oratori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus multis gradibus,</hi> as, <hi>Cicero praeſtat omnes oratores multis gradibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May not an adiectiue of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitiue degree with</hi> magis, <hi>or</hi> minus, <hi>haue an ablutiue caſe after it, as well as one of the comparatiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: ſo <hi>Terence</hi> in <hi>Eunucho. Hoc nemo fuit minus ineptus, nec magis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerus quiſquam</hi> .i. <hi>quam hic. &amp;</hi> Virg. <hi>O luce magis dilecta ſorori</hi> .i. <hi>quam lux.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the conſtruction of Pronounes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not</hi> Meus, <hi>and</hi> Noſter, <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vſed paſſiuely?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: <hi>Plaut. in Pen. ſc. Negotij Ecce odium meum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid me vis? pro, odium mei;</hi> twice in the ſame Scene.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:2017:59"/> Cicero pro Roſc. Amer. <hi>Haec conficta arbitror à poetis eſſe vt effictos mores nostros in alienos perſonis, expreſſam<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> imaginam nostram</hi> (.i. <hi>noſtri) vitae quotidianae videremus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> minus est ſpartiates Agefilaus ille prohibendus, qui neque pictam ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fictam imaginem ſuam</hi> (.i. <hi>ſui) paſſus eſt.</hi> Idem.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Et digna ſpeculo fiat imaego tua</hi> .i. <hi>tui. Mart.</hi> This is to bee obſerued, not imitated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not proper and appellatiue nounes ſometimes put in ſtead of pronounes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: <hi>Plautus in Paenul. ſcen, ſatis ſpectatum.</hi> puts <hi>ſyncerastum pro me,</hi> and <hi>Tuus amicus,</hi> for, <hi>Ego.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Milph. <hi>Heus ſynceraste.</hi> Sync. <hi>Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerastum qui vocat?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mi. <hi>Tuus amicus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not</hi> Noſter <hi>ſometimes put for</hi> Meus &amp; contrà?</p>
               <p>Yes: as for example. <hi>Noſtrum conſilium iure laudandum eſt quod meos ciues ſeruis armatis obijci nolue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim. Cicer.</hi> where <hi>noſtrum</hi> is put for <hi>meum. —Strati<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> per herbam.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:2017:59"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hic meus eſt dixere dies.</hi> Senec. in Suaſor. 2. where <hi>Meus</hi> is put for <hi>Noſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not relatiue pronounes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times put for reciprocall,</hi> &amp; contrà?</p>
               <p>Yes: as for example. <hi>Principio generi animantium omni eſt à natura tributum vt ſe, vitam, corpuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, declinet<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> quae ei</hi> .i. <hi>Sibi nociturae videantur.</hi> Cic.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Praeceptor amat diſcipulos ipſum</hi> (.i. <hi>ſe) excitantes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non petit vt illum</hi> (.i. <hi>ſe) miſerum putetis. Quintil.</hi> Here relatiues are put for reciprocals.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plaut. in Capt. ſcen. Quo illum. Is eſt ſeruus ipſe, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> praeter ſe</hi> (.i. <hi>ipſum) vnquam ei ſeruus fuit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reſpice Laerten vt iam ſua</hi> (.i. <hi>eius) lumina conda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Non ex oratione, ſed ſuis ex mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſpectare debetis pro, eius.</hi> Cicer. here reciprocals are put for rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How are thoſe two rules in</hi> Linacer, <hi>and</hi> Lilly <hi>to bee reconciled.</hi> Ipſe ex pronominibus ſolum trium perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:2017:60"/> ſignificationem repraeſentat. <hi>And,</hi> Idem etiam omnibus perſonis iungi poteſt: <hi>they ſeeme to contradict each other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus. <hi>Ipſe</hi> onely of all thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounes, which truly and properly are pronounes, or which are ſimple pronounes, doth repreſent the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of three perſons: but <hi>Idem</hi> is no ſimple pronoune but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, not a naturall and genuine pronoune, but addititious, as <hi>Lilly</hi> ſaith: one of theſe diſtinctions muſt be admitted or elſe a manifeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction cannot be auoided.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If it bee true that onely</hi> ego, <hi>and</hi> nos, <hi>be of the firſt perſon onely, as is ſet downe in the Engliſh Rudiments: and</hi> Idem, <hi>and</hi> Ipſe, <hi>doe repreſent the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of three perſons, according to your diſtinction. How comes it to paſſe that we finde in</hi> Tully, is, <hi>in the first perſon, as,</hi> Is nullo in loco praedoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus iam pares eſſe poteramus: <hi>and in Liuie,</hi> De pace agitur, agimuſque ij quorum &amp; maxime intereſt pacem eſſe: <hi>and,</hi> Vidiſtis in vincula duci v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſi
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:2017:60"/> eum, qui a ſingulis vobis peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula depulerim.</p>
               <p>Since the pronoune <hi>idem</hi> is vſed in three perſons, which is compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of <hi>is,</hi> &amp; the ſyllabical particle <hi>dem</hi> I am of opinion that <hi>is,</hi> the ſimple pronoune may be vſed ſo likewiſe, as appeareth by the precedent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Since wee may very eaſily erre in the vſe of Pronounes reciprocall, what rules haue you to ſteare and direct vs in the right vſe of them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Diuers; for which you are behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to <hi>Rodolphus Goclenius</hi> in his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations of the Latine tongue, which for memory ſake I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In a ſimple reciprocation <hi>.i.</hi> ſuch as is made with one verbe, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noune of the firſt or ſecond perſon is neuer added to the verbe, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes one of the third: for we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay, <hi>Ego fui ſecum,</hi> but <hi>cum eo,</hi> nor, <hi>Tu nouisti ſuum fratrem,</hi> but <hi>eius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. A reciprocall pronoune reflects
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:2017:61"/> the action of the verbe vpon it ſelfe as the agent: as, <hi>mulier ſibi nimium placet</hi> .i. <hi>ſibi muliere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. When the poſſeſſour workes vpon the thing poſſeſſed, or the thing poſſeſſed vpon the poſſeſſor, the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſiue <hi>ſuus</hi> is vſed: <hi>ſaepe in magistrum ſcelera redierunt ſua. Senec.</hi> and, <hi>&amp; ſua riſerunt ſecula Meomdem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In a compound reciprocation <hi>.i.</hi> ſuch as is made with many verbes, when the action of the verbe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing is reflected vpon the perſon of the verbe afore going, it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by <hi>ſui,</hi> as <hi>Caeſar rogat vt veniam ad ſe</hi> .i. <hi>ad Caeſarem rogantem. Rogat vt ignoſcam ſibi</hi> .i. <hi>ſibi roganti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. When in the conſtruction of two verbes, the action of the latter verbe paſſeth vpon the perſon of the former, as the poſſeſſor, <hi>ſuus</hi> is vſed. <hi>Rogat me vt ſuum</hi> (.i. <hi>eius ipſius qui rogat) instituam filium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. The actiue conſtruction may be changed into the paſſiue by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocall pronoune: as wee may ſay, <hi>Antonium deſeruerunt ſui collegae,</hi> and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:2017:61"/> 
                  <hi>Aut. deſertus eſt a ſuis collegis. Amat patrem filius ſuis,</hi> and, <hi>Amatur pater a filio ſuo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the conſtruction of Verbes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is the conſtruction of the infinitiue moode of a verbe ſubſtantiue the ſame after a verbe perſonall and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: except an accuſatiue caſe be expreſſed before the infinitiue of a verbe ſubſtantiue, which is gouerned of a verbe perſonall, the word which followes ſhall not be the accuſatiue, but the nominatiue; as, wee cannot ſay, <hi>Malo eſſe diuitem,</hi> though <hi>me</hi> be vnderſtood, but <hi>malo eſſe diues,</hi> but when <hi>me</hi> is expreſſed, wee ſay, <hi>malo me eſſe diuitem:</hi> but if an infinitiue be gouerned of a verbe imperſonall, the word that follows the infinitiue, may be the accuſatiue caſe, though the word comming before it be not expreſſed; for wee may ſay, <hi>Iuuat
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:2017:62"/> eſſe diſertos,</hi> as well as <hi>Iuuat nos eſſe diſertos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In thoſe examples,</hi> Adoleſcentis eſt maiores natu reuereri; <hi>and,</hi> Regum eſt parcere ſubiectis, <hi>is</hi> eſt <hi>a verb per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall or imperſonall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a verbe imperſonall, and therefore theſe examples are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed, they belong to the firſt rule of imperſonals, <hi>Intereſt, refert, &amp; eſt,</hi> and there <hi>Lilly</hi> hath ſet downe a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell example: <hi>Prudentis eſt multa diſſimulare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What rule haue you for this conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> Commendo te virtutis, vitupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ignauiae, caſtigo negligentiae, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror prudentiae, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In theſe and the like, there is a <hi>Graeciſme, cauſa,</hi> or <hi>ergô,</hi> is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> often amongſt the Greekes: as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>i.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Beatum te praedico prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fidem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In that of Terence,</hi> Rerum ſuarum ſa tagit; <hi>why doth</hi> ſatagit <hi>gouerne a genetiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The genetiue caſe ſeemes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:2017:62"/> vpon the particle <hi>ſat,</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; and ſo the verbe being of it ſelfe a compound, and one; by reaſon of conſtruction is diuided.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What verbes gouerne a datiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, and all of the like or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſignification: <hi>Commodo, compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, noreo, do, comparo, reddo, polliceor, ſoluo, confudo, obtempero, dico impero, &amp; indignor, minor, ac iraſcor, adulor, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What kinde of datiue doe theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly gouerne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A datiue of the perſon, not of the thing, vnleſſe the thing take vpon it the nature of a perſon; as, <hi>ponti indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur Araxes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What prepoſitions be thoſe wherewith verbes compounded gouerne a datiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe in this hexamiter:
<q>Ad, prae, con, ob, &amp; in, ſimul hae, poſt, ante, ſub, inter.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth not</hi> habeo <hi>put for</hi> eſt <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne a datiue caſe, as well as</hi> eſt <hi>for</hi> habeo?</p>
               <p>Yes: as for example, <hi>Eſt mihi lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibrio, habeo illum ludibrio. Habeo vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptat
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:2017:63"/> literarum ſtudia, literarum ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia ſunt (mihi) voluptati.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> Praeuineo <hi>gouerne an accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue caſe, though it be compounded with</hi> prae, <hi>as</hi> Lilly <hi>tels vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it is a barbarous word, not found in any pure writer, or Lexico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If all verbes tranſitiue gouerne an accuſatiue caſe, how is it that we reade in</hi> Plautus, Conſequor <hi>with a datiue, as,</hi> Voluptati meror vt comes conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur?</p>
               <p>In this there is a greciſme, for the Greekes vſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſequor,</hi> with a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, as <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: ſo they ſay, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: and <hi>Plautus</hi> elſewhere, <hi>decere alicui:</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> hath the like greciſme, <hi>Comitari huic viae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe any verbes of asking gouerne an ablatiue caſe without a praepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: and therefore theſe words, <hi>cum praepoſitione</hi> ſhould be added to that rule, <hi>verba rogandi interdum mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant alterum, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In that example,</hi> Eſt virtus placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:2017:63"/> abſtinuiſſe bonis: <hi>is</hi> bonis <hi>the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue caſe, as</hi> Lilly <hi>informes vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Linacer de Emend. ſtruct. Lat. p,</hi> 267. <hi>l.</hi> 4. ſaith it is the ablatiue caſe, and I rather ſide with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In that example,</hi> Deforme exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabat quos dignitate praeſtaret, ab ijs virtutibus ſuperari: <hi>doth either of thoſe verbes gouerne an ablatiue caſe of the meaſure of exceeding, according to the rule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: thoſe verbes doe gouerne an ablatiue caſe of the matter of exceſſe, not of the meaſure of exceeding, this or the like example would better fitthe rule, <hi>Multis paraſangis omnes ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores precurrit Cicero.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of an Adiectiue gouerning three ablatiue caſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Can any one adiectiue gouerne three ablatiue caſes, according to three ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall rules in Grammer?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as in this example, <hi>Oxonia eſt inſignior Louanio literarum ſtudijs multis paraſangis.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:2017:64"/>
               <head>Of Verbes gouerning diuerſe of the ſame caſes by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall rules of Grammer.</head>
               <p>Can you giue an example of a verbe gouerning three datiue caſes?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as for example,</hi> Neroni (<hi>.i.</hi> a Nerone) probis viris crimini vertitur innocentia.</p>
               <p>Can any one verbe gouerne fiue ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue caſes, according to the rules of Grammer?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as for example;</hi> Ab artifice arte fabrili ſumma diligentia politis pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibus ex vlmeo ligno lectulos fieri iuſſit Titius.</p>
               <p>Can a verbe gouerne three ablatiue caſes with three prepoſitions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as for example;</hi> Accuſatur de furto a vicino ſummo cum rigore.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:2017:64"/>
               <head>Of the Conſtruction of the Infinitiue Moode.</head>
               <p>If two verbes come together, ſhall the latter be alwayes of the Infinitiue moode?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No: ſometimes two verbes are ioyned together in the ſame tenſe and number by an Hyphen. as,</hi> quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam te eſſe dicam-feram. Varro apud Noniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Reddas-restituas, <hi>amongſt the Lawyers.</hi> Qui fecerit ſculpſerit Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destinus: <hi>ſo</hi> Vtimini-foruimini, <hi>whence the ſubſtantiue</hi> vſus fructus.</p>
               <p>May not ſometimes two verbes of the infinitiue moode be ioyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as for example,</hi> Ter. in And. Sc. Adhuc. Dare bibere: <hi>and</hi> dixit Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconſultus non oportere ius ciuile ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniari neque verba captare, ſed qua mente quid diceretur animaduertere conuenire. <hi>So</hi> Dico vti frui licere.</p>
               <p>Is not the infinitiue moode ſometimes vſed as well for the preſent tenſe of the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:2017:65"/> Indicatiue, as for the preter tenſe, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terimperfect tence?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as for example,</hi> Virg. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid. <hi>10.</hi> — Multi ſeruare recurſus,</p>
               <p>Languentis pelagi, &amp; breuibus ſe cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere ſaltu. <hi>where</hi> ſeruare <hi>is put for ſeruant,</hi> credere <hi>for</hi> credunt. <hi>So</hi> Ouid. <hi>4.</hi> Metam. — Rutulis collucent igni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aedes falſaque ſaeuarum ſimulachra vlulare ferarum: <hi>where</hi> vlulare <hi>is put for</hi> vtulant.</p>
               <p>Saluſt. Rurſus Imperator contra po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulata Bocchi nuntios mittit, ille proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re partem, alia abnuere, eo modo ab v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traque miſſis, remiſſiſque nuntijs tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus procedere, &amp; ex Metelli voluntate bellum intactum trahi: <hi>where</hi> proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, abnuere, procedere, trahi, <hi>are put for</hi> probat, abnuit procedit, trahitur.</p>
               <p>Are not verbes of the infinite moode, as alſo verbes finite, vſed ſometimes as nounes, and with the ſame conſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as in theſe examples: Firſt, Verbes finite are vſed as Nounes.</hi> Tull. pro Mur. illud, licet conſulere, perdidiſtis. Aue mihi dixit <hi>.i.</hi> ſalutem. Liu. l. <hi>6.</hi> faxo, ne iuuet vox ista veto <hi>.i.</hi>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:2017:65"/> ne iuuet prohibitio. Plaut. in Paen. Sc. Negotij. Si tacuiſſes, iam istuc Taceo non natum foret. Sapientia vſque ad Plaudite viuendum, in Cat. Mai.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, verbes of the infinitiue moode are vſed for nounes.</hi> Virg. in <hi>9.</hi> Ille ſuo moriens dat habere nepoti. Cic. Inhibere illud tuum quod valde mihi arriſerat, vehementer diſplicet. Perſ. Sat. <hi>1.</hi> Sed fas Tunc cum ad canici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em, &amp; nostrum illud viuere triste. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pexi: <hi>where wee may note alſo that the prepoſition</hi> ad <hi>is praefixed before</hi> viuere. Ipſum illud peccare quoque te verteris vnum eſt. Cic.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of conſtruction by a Periphraſis.</head>
               <p>Doe not pure latine Authors ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make a Periphraſis of a verbe, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne the ſame caſe which the verbe it ſelfe would doe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as</hi> Ter. Id ſtudioſe dat operam. <hi>.i.</hi> id curat. Id ne eſtis autores mihi? <hi>.i.</hi> idne ſuadetis mihi. Idem. Caeſar Senatui dicto audiens futurus <hi>i.</hi> obtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraturus.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:2017:66"/> Cic. Fac me has res certio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem <hi>.i.</hi> edoce me has res. Idem. Quid tibi hanc rem curatio eſt? <hi>.i.</hi> quid hanc rem curas. Plaut. Quid malum tibi istanc tactio eſt? <hi>.i.</hi> quid tangis eam. Idem.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of conſtruction by Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>May not the word which might be put in the ſame caſe with the word wherewith it is ioyned by appoſition be put in the datiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: and that very elegantly, as <hi>Cui nunc cognomen Iülo. Virg. Eſt illi nomen Capitoni. Cic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is it not neceſſary ſometimes that in Appoſition the ſame gender and number be obſerued?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: for we muſt ſay, <hi>Voluptas perpetuae comes ſummi boni,</hi> not <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus. Manus vltrix,</hi> not <hi>vltor, vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus aſſertrix,</hi> not <hi>aſſertor. Inuentri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces literarum Athenae,</hi> not <hi>Inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What if the diuers gender of a noune
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:2017:66"/> ſubstantiue, whioh is called</hi> ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuum mobile <hi>.i. ſuch a one as is vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in termination, and ſex, as</hi> Magiſter, &amp; magiſtra, diſcipulus, diſcipula <hi>be to be ioyned by Appoſition with a word of the neuter gender, is it to be vſed in the maſculine, or in the feminine gender?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the maſculine, as the more worthy; as <hi>Tempus Magiſter arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; diſcipulus rerum,</hi> not <hi>diſcipula,</hi> or <hi>magiſtra,</hi> but if the ſubſtantiue to be coupled be not <hi>ſubstantiuum mobile,</hi> ſometimes a noune of the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minine gender may be added, as <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum nota animi, vitium labes animi.</hi> Sometimes of the maſculine, as <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num abſynthites, vel aromatites</hi> .i. <hi>aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matibus conditum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When may ſubſtantiues coupled in the ſame caſe by Appoſition be of diuers numbers?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Either when one of the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues wants the plurall or ſingular number, as <hi>Diuitiae gluten amicorum. Paſſer deliciae:</hi> or is a noune colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue, as <hi>Angeli agmen forte:</hi> or
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:2017:67"/> ſome one ſingle thing either ioyned with others, or multiplied, is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, as <hi>Nata mea vices. Vxor mea gaudia. Pulmones instrumentum</hi> (not <hi>instrumenta (reſpirationis:</hi> for there is but one lung in a liuing creature, but the ancients ſaid <hi>pulmones</hi> in the plurall number, becauſe that part of the body which drawes in, and lets forth the breath is cleft, as the hoof of an Oxe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are ſubstantiues ioyned by Appoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alwaies put in the ſame caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: the latter ſubſtantiue which doth explaine or declare the former is ſometimes put in the ablatiue caſe, and the word explained in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or datiue; as, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iuis Patauij vrbe ſcientiarum laude celeberrima. Romae lupinari communi habitas. Oxoniae A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cademia clariſſima crematus eſt Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus. Lacedaemoni oppido inſigni ſeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus honor maximus habebatur.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:2017:67"/>
               <head>Of the conſtruction of Gerunds and Supines.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that rule generally true, Gerunds and Supines gouerne the ſame caſe that the verbes that they come of?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it is to be vnderſtood onely of gerunds ſignifying actiuely, and the firſt ſupines: for gerunds which ſignifie paſſiuely, and the latter ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines are ſcarce to be found with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny caſes after them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may this, and the like Engliſh phraſes be rendred in Latine,</hi> viz. <hi>I came in dinner time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Very elegantly by the gerund in <hi>dum,</hi> with the prepoſition <hi>inter;</hi> as, <hi>veni inter prandendum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In theſe formes of ſpeech,</hi> accuſatum oportuit factum oportet: volo da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum; <hi>how may it appeare</hi> that accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, factum, datum, <hi>are participles, not ſupines?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus: becauſe wee finde parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples varied in all genders in this
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:2017:68"/> forme of ſpeech, whereas ſupines want all genders, and flexion. <hi>Ter. in Heauton. Interemptam oportuit, &amp; in Andr. Nonne prius communicatum oportuit. Sic, cupio hunc defenſum, &amp; hanc defenſam.</hi> Here the verbe <hi>eſſe</hi> is to be ſupplied.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What doe you thinke of theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines,</hi> Do venum, do nuptum, <hi>which</hi> Lilly <hi>ſaith haue</hi> latentem mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nuptum</hi> ſignifies<note n="*" place="margin">Nubit vxor, ducit vxorem vir.</note> paſſiuely: <hi>do nuptum,</hi> I giue in marriage, or to be married. It is queſtinable whether <hi>venum</hi> be a ſupine of <hi>veneo,</hi> or an aduerbe like to <hi>peſſum;</hi> the analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie ſeemes to inſinuate ſo much; as wee ſay <hi>peſſundare,</hi> and <hi>peſſum da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re;</hi> ſo wee ſay <hi>venundare,</hi> and <hi>venum dare, ſed de hoc amplian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In thoſe examples,</hi> Actum eſt, Itum eſt, Ceſſatum eſt, <hi>is the firſt ſupine put abſolutely with the verbe</hi> eſt, <hi>as</hi> Lilly <hi>tels vs?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: herein hee is fouly deceiued, hee might as well ſay, <hi>placitum
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:2017:68"/> eſt, libitum eſt, puditum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> are Supines, which he affirms are Verbs imperſonall of the paſſiue voyce, in his rules of Etymologie, touching Imperſonals, and ſuch are theſe alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Place.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is that rule:</hi> Omne verbum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit genitiuum proprij nominis loci in quo fit actio, &amp;c. <hi>true, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all proper names of places of the first, or ſecond declenſion, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular number?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: it extends only to proper names of Cities, and Townes, not to vaſt Regions: for wee may not ſay, <hi>Numidiae acriter pugnatum est,</hi> but in <hi>Numidia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By what rule of</hi> Lillies <hi>Syntaxis, is</hi> terra-marique <hi>the ablatiue caſe, in that of Cicero;</hi> Quantas ille res ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, mariquegeſſerat?</p>
               <p>There is not any rule for that manner of conſtruction, but it is of kin to that of <hi>ruri,</hi> and <hi>rure.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:2017:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is</hi> domi <hi>neuer read with any other genitiue caſe, except</hi> meae, tuae, &amp;c. <hi>as</hi> Lilly <hi>affirmes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: it is read with other poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiues alſo: we may ſay, <hi>Domi ſubur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banae, regiae, paterna,</hi> as well as <hi>Domi meae, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of verbes Imperſonall.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In thoſe clauſes,</hi> vt videre eſt, vt legere eſt apud Ariſtotelem. Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt te fallere cuiquam, Virg. <hi>How comes it to paſſe that</hi> eſt <hi>is put for</hi> licet?</p>
               <p>It is an imitation of the Greeks, who put <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>licet.</hi> ſo <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (vel <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Participles.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are all participles changed not nounes, when they ceaſe to ſignifie Time?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So <hi>Lilly</hi> teacheth vs in his Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar.</p>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:2017:69"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why then doth hee in his Syntaxis put downe, that</hi> exoſus, peroſus, <hi>are conſtrued with an accuſatiue caſe, when they ſignifie actiuely; and a datiue when they ſignifie paſſiuely; and</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taeſus <hi>with an accuſatiue: Why are</hi> Natus, prognatus, &amp;c. <hi>ſaid to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrued with an ablatiue caſe as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, when as none of theſe doe ſignifie Time any more then</hi> homo laudatus, <hi>or</hi> puer amandus?</p>
               <p>It may be thoſe two rules of <hi>exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, peroſus, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>natus, &amp;c.</hi> are exceptions from that generall rule placed before them, <hi>viz. Participio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum voces cum fiunt nomina, &amp;c.</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiples when they are made nounes require a genitiue caſe: and they are made nounes foure wayes: firſt, when they gouerne not the ſame caſe that the verbes doe that they come of. Secondly, when they are compounded with prepoſitions that their verbs cannot be compounded with. Thirdly, when they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared. Fourthly, when they leaue of
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:2017:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> to ſignifie difference of Time: in this reſpect <hi>exoſus, peroſus, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>natus, &amp;c.</hi> it may bee are excepted from the precedent generall rule.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It may be ſo: but this is onely a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecture to ſaue</hi> Lillies <hi>credit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Indeede I muſt needes confeſſe that <hi>Lilly</hi> is not ſo diſtinct, punctuall, and exact as he ſhould bee, but wee muſt make the beſt of him, till ſome other more Grammarian ſhall compoſe vs a better Grammar: and here I will adde this alſo, that that generall of participials gouerning a genitiue, is not to be vnderſtood of any participials in <hi>Dus,</hi> or <hi>Tus,</hi> for they gouerne a datiue caſe: as, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros celebrandus omnibus poetis. Hoc eſt notum lippis &amp; tonſoribus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The conſtruction of Aduerbs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth</hi> contrà, <hi>being put without caſe, and ſo becomming an aduerbe onely, retaine and not augment the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:2017:70"/> which it had, being a prepoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as other prepoſitions doe,</hi> coram, poſt, clam, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>No: for it doth not onely ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie oppoſition, as, <hi>ſi homo eſt ridere poteſt, &amp; contrà, ſi non eſt homo ridere non poteſt,</hi> but reciprocation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, or alternation: as, <hi>ſi ridere potest est homo, &amp; contrà, ſi est homo poteſt ridere,</hi> where <hi>contrà</hi> is equiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to <hi>viciſſim,</hi> or <hi>viciſſim retro:</hi> as alſo in this of <hi>Terence: In eo oblecto me ſolùm, &amp; carum ille vt item contrà me habeat facio ſedulo:</hi> &amp; Virg. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neid. 1. <hi>Aeolus haec contrà:</hi> where <hi>Aeolus</hi> in his ſpeech doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict, but aſſent to <hi>Iuno.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May not an Aduerbe, as well as an Adiectiue put partitiuely, gouerne a genitiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as for example. <hi>Manuum fortiùs ſe habet dextra. Omnium pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netarum ſol ſplendet lucidiſſimè.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Is not the aduerbe</hi> Parum <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times added very elegantly to an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectiue, and ſometimes to a ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:2017:71"/>
               <p>Yes: as <hi>Cic. ad Att. Vide ne dum pudet te parum optimatem eſſe, parum diligenter quod optimum est eligas,</hi> Quint. Inſt. l. 5. <hi>Mollis, &amp; parum vici ſigna.</hi> Scal. in Exerc. <hi>Parum Philoſophi, parum Phyſici. Minus, vel parum firma fuit valetudine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In thoſe examples:</hi> Caſtra propiùs vrbem mouentur; <hi>and,</hi> Proximè Hiſpaniam ſunt Mauri, <hi>are,</hi> Propiùs, <hi>and</hi> Proximè, <hi>properly aduerbs, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerning an accuſatiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I thinke not: they rather ſeeme to be prepoſitions compared gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning an accuſ. as the originall word, or theame <hi>Prope</hi> doth. <hi>Propiùs</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee deriued of <hi>propior</hi> in this Syntaxis; for wee finde in <hi>Liuie, propior vero propiùs vero,</hi> and <hi>propior</hi> is the comparatiue of <hi>propis,</hi> an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute word, as <hi>prior</hi> of <hi>pris.</hi> So <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clen. Problem. Gram. l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 145.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May not an Aduerbe deriued of an Adiectiue which gouerneth an Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiue caſe with a Prepoſition, gouerne the ſame caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as for example. <hi>Poeta ſi ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:2017:71"/> ad delectationem, Orator ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Philoſophus ad vitam dicat, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleſſe munus ſuum videntur.</hi> Iuſt. Lipſius.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In that clauſe of the fable of</hi> Eſops <hi>Cocke,</hi> granum hordei mallem om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus gemmis; <hi>why is</hi> gemmis <hi>the ablatiue caſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the ablatiue caſe by reaſon of the word <hi>magis,</hi> which lyeth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly couched in the word <hi>mallem,</hi> which may bee reſolued into <hi>magis vellem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are not ſometimes nounes put for aduerbs,</hi> &amp; contrà?</p>
               <p>Yes: firſt, Nounes put for Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes. <hi>Nullus pro Non,</hi> by the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure called <hi>Antemeria. Philoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus nullus venit.</hi> Cic. <hi>Quaerit ex proximo vicino num feriae quaedam piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum eſſent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vox hominem ſonat <hi>.i.</hi> huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niter. <hi>Virg.</hi> Viuunt Baccha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia <hi>.i.</hi> Baccha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naliter. Iuu. <hi>vide</hi> Linac. de Emend. ſtruct. Lat. l. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>94.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>quod eos nullos vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</hi> Idem. <hi>Etſi nullus diceris.</hi> Terent. <hi>At tu dolebis cum rogaberis nulla. Catullus.</hi> This is an elegant kinde of expreſſion. <hi>Nemo pro Non.</hi> Tac. 4. Ann. <hi>Ferrum, &amp; caedes quonam modo occultaretur nemo reperiebat.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:2017:72"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Multus pro multum. Multus in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris. In opere multus.</hi> Saluſt. <hi>Totus pro totaliter. Totus diſpliceo mihi.</hi> Ter. <hi>Totus eſt alienus à Phyſicis.</hi> Cicer. <hi>Plurimus pro plurimùm. In toto pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus orbe legor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Aduerbs put for nounes. <hi>Satis vir, pro magnanimo.</hi> Senec. <hi>Pluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam viri, pro virorum partes exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus. Parum fides, pro parua.</hi> Plaut.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In thoſe examples.</hi> Multò aliter, paulo ſecus, longe ſecus: <hi>are</hi> multò, paulò, longè, <hi>ablatiue caſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lilly</hi> did ill to ſurmiſe ſo; that rule is altogether ſuperfluous; in like manner hee was deceiued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when in the rules of Adie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiues, he affirmed, that in that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Quantò doctior es, tantò te ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras ſubmiſſius; quantò,</hi> and <hi>tantò,</hi> were of the ablatiue caſe, whereas they are aduerbs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>May not the forme, or manner of a thing, bee put after an aduerbe in the ablatiue caſe, as well as after an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectiue?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:2017:72"/>
               <p>Yes: as, <hi>agit fortiter verbis, factis ignauè.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Coniunctions.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In thoſe Clauſes of</hi> Plautus <hi>and Terence.</hi> Abſque hoc eſſet, abſque eo foret; <hi>how come the verbes to bee of the ſubiunctiue moode?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By reaſon of the particle <hi>ſi</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, which is to bee ſupplyed, to make perfect conſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After what verbes are thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles vſed,</hi> quod, vt, ne.</p>
               <p>After theſe, and the like: for we ſay, <hi>Puto quod, Iubeo vt, Metuo ne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe</hi> ac, <hi>and</hi> atque, <hi>alwayes come before in a clauſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alwayes, except in compoſition: as, <hi>ſimulac, ſimulat<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</hi> after the greeke manner, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doth not a coniunction ſometimes gouerne a caſe as a noune?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yes: as <hi>Virg. Illius ergô Veni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: Amoris, Honoris, Virtutis ergô.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:2017:73"/>
               <head>Of Prepoſitions.</head>
               <p>Is not <hi>procul,</hi> when it is conſtrued with Caſe, a Prepoſition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some learned men thinke ſo: it is read with and accuſatiue or abla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue caſe; as in</hi> Curtius. Procul vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem. <hi>in</hi> Liuie, Locus procul muros; <hi>and in the ſame Authors:</hi> Procul muro. Procul mari. Procul diſcordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus armis. <hi>Virg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Are not ſometimes prepoſitions put before other prepoſitions?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as,</hi> Vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſub obſcurum noctis. Vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ex Aethiopia. De Quinto fratre nuntij nobis tristes venerant ex ante diem Nonarum Iuniarum vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Calend. Septemb. <hi>The titles of chapters amongſt the Ciuilians, are.</hi> De in ius vocando. De in diem addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione: <hi>and,</hi> Gell. <hi>1. 10.</hi> In de Analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia libro ſcriptum eſt.</p>
               <p>Is not a prepoſition ſometimes put for a coniunction, and an aduerbe for a prepoſition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: firſt, a prepoſition is put for a conjunction in</hi> Saluſt. Praeter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:2017:73"/> rum capitalium condemnatis: praeter <hi>for</hi> praeterquam.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, an aduerbe for a prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in</hi> Virg. Aen. <hi>7.</hi> Tali intus tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plo diuum, patriaque latinus ſede ſedens, vide Linac. de Emen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. ſtruct. Lat. Ser. l. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>109.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not a coniunction ſometimes put in the place of a pronounce with a prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: as,</hi> A me vero ita diligitur, vt tibi vni concedam praeterea nemini <hi>.i.</hi> praeter te. Cic. Eundem ab hostibus metui, praeterea neminem <hi>i.</hi> praeter eum. Idem.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of an Interiection.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In this ſentence;</hi> Egregium vero Philoſophum qui inter ſolem, &amp; ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quid intereſſet parum curauit intelligere: <hi>why is</hi> Egregium Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophum the accuſatiue caſe?</p>
               <p>Becauſe therein there is an ellipſis of the interiection <hi>O.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What interiections gouerne an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiue caſe, beſides thoſe expreſſed in</hi> Lillies <hi>Syntaxe?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:2017:74"/>
               <p>Theſe: <hi>Eheu, hem, apage;</hi> as <hi>Eheu conditionem huius temporis. Cic. Hem.</hi> being an Ironicall interiection; as, <hi>Hem aſtutias. Ter.</hi> O ſubtile deuiſe <hi>Apage te. Ter. Apage istiuſmodi ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem. Plaut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are all things that are written by the ancient Authors to be exactly exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and ſcanned according to rule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>No: for ſome had faults which of ſet purpoſe they loued &amp; defended: <hi>Tantus error eſt in omnibus ſtudijs, maxime in eloquentia, cuius regula in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certa eſt, vt vitia quidam ſua &amp; intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, &amp; ament:</hi> there is ſo great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in all ſtudies, eſpecially in elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, the rule of which is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, in ſo much as ſome both know and affect their fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith <hi>Seneca:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>2.</hi> Contr. <hi>20.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect. Virg <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Georg. verſum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> O qui m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dis in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>allibus, Hemi.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbis licenter in carmini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus vſus eſt Naſo, in quibus non ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit vitia ſua, ſed amauit, &amp;c. Ouid</hi> was ſomewhat bold, and licentious in the vſe of ſome words in his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; wherein, he was not ignorant of the fault, but liked it, &amp; often would ſay that a Mole misbecame not a</p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2017:74"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:2017:75"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:2017:75" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
